<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-20T12:39:58+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Chapter One Mag</title><subtitle>This is the archive of ChapterOneMag.com, a blog project run by Christina Wunder from 2014-2019.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Wir müssen dort Druck machen wo die Entscheidungen getroffen werden</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wir-mussen-dort-druck-machen-wo-die-entscheidungen-getroffen-werden/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wir müssen dort Druck machen wo die Entscheidungen getroffen werden" /><published>2019-03-25T10:34:22+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-25T10:34:22+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wir-mussen-dort-druck-machen-wo-die-entscheidungen-getroffen-werden</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wir-mussen-dort-druck-machen-wo-die-entscheidungen-getroffen-werden/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.delara-burkhardt.eu/&quot;&gt;Delara Burkhardt&lt;/a&gt; ist Kandidatin der SPD für die Europawahl. Als heute 26-Jährige ist sie schon immer in und mit der EU aufgewachsen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Die EU war irgendwie immer da. Und selbst, wenn es mal Probleme gab, irgendwie ging es immer voran. Diese Gewissheit ist vorbei.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt so einige Gewissheiten mit denen es vorbei ist. Es ist zum Beispiel nicht mehr gewiss, ob unsere Rente mal zum Überleben ausreichen wird. Oder ob unser Planet dann überhaupt noch für Menschen bewohnbar ist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es ist nicht mehr gewiss, dass junge Menschen es einmal besser haben werden als ihre Eltern - das Gegenteil ist der Fall. Junge Menschen zählen heute zu den Menschen in Europa, die am stärksten von Armut bedroht sind: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Young_people_-_social_inclusion&amp;amp;oldid=417981&quot;&gt;fast ein Drittel der jungen Menschen in Europa&lt;/a&gt; (28%) sind von Armut oder sozialer Ausgrenzung gefährdet. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/products-eurostat-news/-/DDN-20190122-1?inheritRedirect=true&quot;&gt;Jede/r zehnte (11%) sogar trotz Vollzeitjob&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und obwohl politische Entscheidungen junge Menschen massiv betreffen, sind sie in der &quot;Entscheider&quot;-Ebene massiv unterrepräsentiert. Sie können nicht ausreichend mitbestimmen wenn es darum geht, die drängenden Fragen unserer Zeit anzugehen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe mit Delara Burkhardt über ihr politisches Engagement gesprochen und wollte wissen: Sind &quot;wir Jungen&quot; selber Schuld? Wie können sich junge Menschen stärker in die Politik einbringen? Und wie macht man bitte eigentlich überhaupt Politik?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-large wp-image-5454&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Delara-Burkhardt-SPD-1024x683.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Delara Burkhardt SPD&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;&quot;Junge Menschen sind nämlich nicht politikverdrossen. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation zu wenig von der Mitarbeit in Parteien angesprochen fühlt, dann müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; - Delara Burkhardt, Europa-Kandidatin der SPD&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Delara, du kandidierst mit 26 um einen Sitz im Europaparlament. Wie bist du zur Politik gekommen? Wie hat es angefangen und wie sieht dein Engagement heute konkret aus?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2008 gab es in Schleswig-Holstein im ganzen Land Schulstreiks, weil die schwarz-gelbe Landesregierung die Zeit bis zum Abitur von neun auf acht Jahre verkürzt hat. Ich fand es nicht richtig, dass diese Entscheidung, die so große Auswirkung auf unsere Zukunft haben sollte, über die Köpfe von uns Schülerinnen und Schülern hinweg getroffen wurde. Da wurde für mich deutlich, dass man für Veränderung auch Verantwortung übernehmen und selbst mit anpacken muss. So funktioniert eine Demokratie. Deshalb entschloss ich mich, einer Partei beizutreten. Da war ich 15 Jahre alt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Wie @delarabur zur Politik gekommen ist? Empörung über die Tatsache, dass Entscheidung über die Zukunft junger Menschen über unsere Köpfe hinweg getroffen werden.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nachdem ich mich mit den Programmen verschiedener Parteien auseinandergesetzt hatte, habe ich mich entschieden, der SPD beizutreten - genauer gesagt deren Jugendorganisation: den Jusos. und bin dann auf verschiedenen Ebenen aktiv geworden. Heute bin ich eine von acht stellvertretenden Bundesvorsitzenden der Jusos und dort für die Themen Internationales und Gleichstellung zuständig. Besonders wichtig war mir dabei immer die Zusammenarbeit mit Zivilgesellschaft, Gewerkschaften und Verbänden. Durch die internationale Arbeit der Jusos habe ich außerdem viele Eindrücke in Europa, aber auch darüber hinaus gesammelt. Ich habe unter anderem Projekte im Nahen Osten, auf dem Balkan und in Nordafrika verantwortet. Ich habe gesehen, was funktioniert, und ich habe auch gesehen, wo wir dringend Veränderungen brauchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sich neben dem Job ehrenamtlich oder politisch zu engagieren kann sehr anstrengend sein. Welche Herausforderungen ergeben sich für dich in der Praxis? Wie lässt sich das trotzdem unter einen Hut bringen?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich denke, man muss lernen, auch mal nein zu sagen. Wenn man es darauf anlegt, kann man jeden Abend auf vielen Veranstaltungen sein und in vielen unterschiedlichen Gremien mitarbeiten. Mir war es immer wichtig, neben meinem politischen Engagement das Studium nicht zu vernachlässigen und den Aufgaben, die ich übernahm auch gerecht zu werden. Deshalb habe ich immer, wenn ich etwas Neues angefangen habe, andere Ämter abgegeben. Das ist manchmal schade, weil es so viele spannende Dinge gibt, bei denen man sich einbringen kann. Aber es ist eben auch wichtig, mal Luft für andere Dinge zu haben. Mir hat außerdem geholfen, dass ich mit Beginn meines Studiums ein Stipendium der &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fes.de/studienfoerderung/bewerbung/&quot;&gt;Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung&lt;/a&gt; erhalten habe. Das hat mir Freiräume für ehrenamtliches Engagement im Studium ermöglicht. Ansonsten hätte ich das in diesem Maße nicht durchziehen können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Unter 30-Jährige machen nur 2% der Abgeordneten in Europa aus – wie können junge Menschen besser in der Politik repräsentiert werden?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In meinem Engagement habe ich gemerkt, dass „Vorbilder“ super wichtig sind. Als ich zu den Jusos kam, war ich beispielsweise die einzige Frau in meinem Kreisverband. Das hat sich zum Glück geändert. Ich bin froh, viele andere Frauen für die Mitarbeit bei den Jusos und in der SPD gewinnen zu können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aber junge Menschen und Frauen sind noch zu wenig in den Strukturen politischer Parteien repräsentiert, und die Parteien stehen in der Pflicht, sich dieses Problem bewusst zu machen. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation zu wenig von der Mitarbeit in Parteien angesprochen fühlt, dann müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten. Junge Menschen sind nämlich nicht politikverdrossen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Junge Menschen sind nicht politikverdrossen - das Interesse ist so groß wie lange nicht mehr, so @delarabur. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation nicht angesprochen fühlt, müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Im Gegenteil, das Interesse ist so groß wie schon lange nicht mehr. Ein gutes Beispiel dafür sind doch die zahlreichen Jugendlichen, die derzeit in ganz Europa für Klimaschutz auf die Straße gehen. Parteien müssen deshalb wieder ein attraktiver Ort werden, um Politik zu gestalten! Die &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bento.de/politik/delara-burkhardt-spd-ueber-die-liste-zur-europawahl-a-615f9198-01a3-4092-9b3e-175ab2bb1bd7&quot;&gt;Jugendquote&lt;/a&gt; ist zum Beispiel ein Instrument, das immer wieder diskutiert wird, um der Missrepräsentanz junger Menschen in den Parlamenten und in der Politik entgegenzuwirken. Die macht für mich aber nur Sinn, wenn es eben auch die Jugendorganisationen sind, die diese Plätze besetzen dürfen. Ansonsten entscheiden wieder Ältere darüber, wer die Jugend vertreten soll. Fürs erste wäre aber schon mal eine Selbstverpflichtung für vielfältigere Listen ein erster Schritt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Eine Jugendquote macht nur Sinn, wenn es auch die Jugendorganisationen sind, die die Plätze besetzen dürfen. Ansonsten entscheiden Ältere darüber, wer die Jugend vertreten soll, sagt @delarabur&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Was macht deine Partei, um junge Menschen besser einzubinden und ihre Interessen zu repräsentieren?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein starkes Signal der SPD war es, mich als Kandidatin der Jusos auf einen aussichtsreichen Platz für die Europawahl zu setzen. In der SPD gibt es Nachwuchsförderungsprogramme, in denen junge Menschen die Möglichkeit bekommen, sich für die politische Arbeit zu wappnen und Einblicke zu bekommen. Ich finde es außerdem wichtig, darüber zu sprechen, wie wir die alltägliche Parteiarbeit attraktiver gestalten können. Man wird ja meistens über politische Themen politisiert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es muss Räume geben, in denen man neben administrativen Dingen auch mal über den Tellerrand gucken und diese aktuellen politischen Themen diskutieren kann. Außerdem sollte es leichter werden, sich aktiv einzubringen und mitzugestalten - ohne dass man dafür gleich in einer politischen Funktion sein muss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Viele junge Menschen interessieren sich verstärkt für Politik – aber dieses Interesse kommt in der (Partei-)Politik oft nicht an. Woran liegt das, warum ist das ein Problem, und wie kann es angegangen werden?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das ist ein Kommunikationsproblem – von beiden Seiten. Gerade die Bewegung &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fridaysforfuture.org/&quot;&gt;Fridays For Future&lt;/a&gt;, aber auch die Gegenmobilisierung zu den geplanten Uploadfiltern in der Debatte um die Urheberschutzreform zeigen, dass ein verstärktes Bewusstsein in unserer Generation erwacht, dass (Europäische) Politik einen enormen Einfluss hat auf die Frage: wie wird unsere Zukunft gestaltet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein gutes Zeichen ist, das sich die jungen Protestbewegungen vor die Parlamente und Ministerien bewegen. Also ein großes Bewusstsein dafür herrscht, das dort diese Entscheidungen getroffen werden. Ich appelliere immer, den Kontakt zur (Partei)politik zu suchen, wenn man möchte, dass das Anliegen gehört wird. Druck machen - dort, wo die Entscheidungen getroffen werden. Gleichzeitig muss auch die Politik viel offener auf solche Jugendbewegungen zugehen, zuhören und das Anliegen ernst nehmen. Ansonsten bleibt die Lebensrealität junger Menschen im politischen Prozess ungehört.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Welche Tipps hättest du für junge Menschen, die sich politisch engagieren möchten, aber nicht wissen wie oder wo sie anfangen sollen?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Überleg dir, welche Themen dir am Herzen liegen und womit du dich einbringen möchtest. Man ist nie zu 100% einer Meinung mit dem Programm einer Partei, aber das Spannende ist: Man kann dafür sorgen, dass sich Programme weiterentwickeln! Nutze diese Chance und suche dir Verbündete, die mit dir für Veränderung und deine Ideen streiten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wenn du deinem 5 oder 10 Jahre jüngeren Ich einen Tipp geben könntest (in Bezug auf politisches Engagement) – was wäre das?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vielleicht wäre es genau das: Sei kreativ und sei mutig für Veränderung einzustehen! Auch wenn Leute, die deine Eltern oder Großeltern sein könnten dir sagen, dass dieses und jenes nicht geht, weil es schon immer so gemacht wurde - lass dich davon nicht unterbuttern, sondern nutze deine Stimme und zeige, dass es eben doch anders geht!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Liebe Delara, vielen Dank für das spannende Interview und viel Erfolg für die Wahl am 26. Mai!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Und Du, liebe Leserin und lieber Leser? Bist Du startklar für die Europawahl am 26. Mai?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wenn du in Deutschland in deinem Heimatort im Wählerverzeichnis eingetragen bist, solltest Du&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/informationen-waehler/wahlbenachrichtigung.html#809a5400-7246-4bb1-b883-02396597b463&quot;&gt; Deine Wahlbenachrichtigung ganz normal per Post&lt;/a&gt; erhalten.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solltest du am 26. Mai verhindert sein, kannst Du &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/informationen-waehler/briefwahl.html#33ef253b-a547-4c24-aa72-d8f0345e5d7e&quot;&gt;eine Briefwahl beantragen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Falls Du (wie ich) nicht mehr in Deutschland gemeldet bist und im Ausland lebst, kannst Du Dich &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/informationen-waehler/deutsche-im-ausland.html&quot;&gt;hier ins Wählerverzeichnis eintragen lassen und alle nötigen Unterlagen beantragen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">Delara Burkhardt ist Kandidatin der SPD für die Europawahl. Als heute 26-Jährige ist sie schon immer in und mit der EU aufgewachsen. &quot;Die EU war irgendwie immer da. Und selbst, wenn es mal Probleme gab, irgendwie ging es immer voran. Diese Gewissheit ist vorbei.&quot; Es gibt so einige Gewissheiten mit denen es vorbei ist. Es ist zum Beispiel nicht mehr gewiss, ob unsere Rente mal zum Überleben ausreichen wird. Oder ob unser Planet dann überhaupt noch für Menschen bewohnbar ist. Es ist nicht mehr gewiss, dass junge Menschen es einmal besser haben werden als ihre Eltern - das Gegenteil ist der Fall. Junge Menschen zählen heute zu den Menschen in Europa, die am stärksten von Armut bedroht sind: fast ein Drittel der jungen Menschen in Europa (28%) sind von Armut oder sozialer Ausgrenzung gefährdet. Jede/r zehnte (11%) sogar trotz Vollzeitjob. Und obwohl politische Entscheidungen junge Menschen massiv betreffen, sind sie in der &quot;Entscheider&quot;-Ebene massiv unterrepräsentiert. Sie können nicht ausreichend mitbestimmen wenn es darum geht, die drängenden Fragen unserer Zeit anzugehen. Ich habe mit Delara Burkhardt über ihr politisches Engagement gesprochen und wollte wissen: Sind &quot;wir Jungen&quot; selber Schuld? Wie können sich junge Menschen stärker in die Politik einbringen? Und wie macht man bitte eigentlich überhaupt Politik? &quot;Junge Menschen sind nämlich nicht politikverdrossen. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation zu wenig von der Mitarbeit in Parteien angesprochen fühlt, dann müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten.&quot; - Delara Burkhardt, Europa-Kandidatin der SPD &amp;nbsp; Delara, du kandidierst mit 26 um einen Sitz im Europaparlament. Wie bist du zur Politik gekommen? Wie hat es angefangen und wie sieht dein Engagement heute konkret aus? 2008 gab es in Schleswig-Holstein im ganzen Land Schulstreiks, weil die schwarz-gelbe Landesregierung die Zeit bis zum Abitur von neun auf acht Jahre verkürzt hat. Ich fand es nicht richtig, dass diese Entscheidung, die so große Auswirkung auf unsere Zukunft haben sollte, über die Köpfe von uns Schülerinnen und Schülern hinweg getroffen wurde. Da wurde für mich deutlich, dass man für Veränderung auch Verantwortung übernehmen und selbst mit anpacken muss. So funktioniert eine Demokratie. Deshalb entschloss ich mich, einer Partei beizutreten. Da war ich 15 Jahre alt. [bctt tweet=&quot;Wie @delarabur zur Politik gekommen ist? Empörung über die Tatsache, dass Entscheidung über die Zukunft junger Menschen über unsere Köpfe hinweg getroffen werden.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Nachdem ich mich mit den Programmen verschiedener Parteien auseinandergesetzt hatte, habe ich mich entschieden, der SPD beizutreten - genauer gesagt deren Jugendorganisation: den Jusos. und bin dann auf verschiedenen Ebenen aktiv geworden. Heute bin ich eine von acht stellvertretenden Bundesvorsitzenden der Jusos und dort für die Themen Internationales und Gleichstellung zuständig. Besonders wichtig war mir dabei immer die Zusammenarbeit mit Zivilgesellschaft, Gewerkschaften und Verbänden. Durch die internationale Arbeit der Jusos habe ich außerdem viele Eindrücke in Europa, aber auch darüber hinaus gesammelt. Ich habe unter anderem Projekte im Nahen Osten, auf dem Balkan und in Nordafrika verantwortet. Ich habe gesehen, was funktioniert, und ich habe auch gesehen, wo wir dringend Veränderungen brauchen. Sich neben dem Job ehrenamtlich oder politisch zu engagieren kann sehr anstrengend sein. Welche Herausforderungen ergeben sich für dich in der Praxis? Wie lässt sich das trotzdem unter einen Hut bringen? Ich denke, man muss lernen, auch mal nein zu sagen. Wenn man es darauf anlegt, kann man jeden Abend auf vielen Veranstaltungen sein und in vielen unterschiedlichen Gremien mitarbeiten. Mir war es immer wichtig, neben meinem politischen Engagement das Studium nicht zu vernachlässigen und den Aufgaben, die ich übernahm auch gerecht zu werden. Deshalb habe ich immer, wenn ich etwas Neues angefangen habe, andere Ämter abgegeben. Das ist manchmal schade, weil es so viele spannende Dinge gibt, bei denen man sich einbringen kann. Aber es ist eben auch wichtig, mal Luft für andere Dinge zu haben. Mir hat außerdem geholfen, dass ich mit Beginn meines Studiums ein Stipendium der Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung erhalten habe. Das hat mir Freiräume für ehrenamtliches Engagement im Studium ermöglicht. Ansonsten hätte ich das in diesem Maße nicht durchziehen können. Unter 30-Jährige machen nur 2% der Abgeordneten in Europa aus – wie können junge Menschen besser in der Politik repräsentiert werden? In meinem Engagement habe ich gemerkt, dass „Vorbilder“ super wichtig sind. Als ich zu den Jusos kam, war ich beispielsweise die einzige Frau in meinem Kreisverband. Das hat sich zum Glück geändert. Ich bin froh, viele andere Frauen für die Mitarbeit bei den Jusos und in der SPD gewinnen zu können. Aber junge Menschen und Frauen sind noch zu wenig in den Strukturen politischer Parteien repräsentiert, und die Parteien stehen in der Pflicht, sich dieses Problem bewusst zu machen. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation zu wenig von der Mitarbeit in Parteien angesprochen fühlt, dann müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten. Junge Menschen sind nämlich nicht politikverdrossen. [bctt tweet=&quot;Junge Menschen sind nicht politikverdrossen - das Interesse ist so groß wie lange nicht mehr, so @delarabur. Wenn sich eine ganze Generation nicht angesprochen fühlt, müssen die Parteien an sich arbeiten.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Im Gegenteil, das Interesse ist so groß wie schon lange nicht mehr. Ein gutes Beispiel dafür sind doch die zahlreichen Jugendlichen, die derzeit in ganz Europa für Klimaschutz auf die Straße gehen. Parteien müssen deshalb wieder ein attraktiver Ort werden, um Politik zu gestalten! Die Jugendquote ist zum Beispiel ein Instrument, das immer wieder diskutiert wird, um der Missrepräsentanz junger Menschen in den Parlamenten und in der Politik entgegenzuwirken. Die macht für mich aber nur Sinn, wenn es eben auch die Jugendorganisationen sind, die diese Plätze besetzen dürfen. Ansonsten entscheiden wieder Ältere darüber, wer die Jugend vertreten soll. Fürs erste wäre aber schon mal eine Selbstverpflichtung für vielfältigere Listen ein erster Schritt. [bctt tweet=&quot;Eine Jugendquote macht nur Sinn, wenn es auch die Jugendorganisationen sind, die die Plätze besetzen dürfen. Ansonsten entscheiden Ältere darüber, wer die Jugend vertreten soll, sagt @delarabur&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Was macht deine Partei, um junge Menschen besser einzubinden und ihre Interessen zu repräsentieren? Ein starkes Signal der SPD war es, mich als Kandidatin der Jusos auf einen aussichtsreichen Platz für die Europawahl zu setzen. In der SPD gibt es Nachwuchsförderungsprogramme, in denen junge Menschen die Möglichkeit bekommen, sich für die politische Arbeit zu wappnen und Einblicke zu bekommen. Ich finde es außerdem wichtig, darüber zu sprechen, wie wir die alltägliche Parteiarbeit attraktiver gestalten können. Man wird ja meistens über politische Themen politisiert. Es muss Räume geben, in denen man neben administrativen Dingen auch mal über den Tellerrand gucken und diese aktuellen politischen Themen diskutieren kann. Außerdem sollte es leichter werden, sich aktiv einzubringen und mitzugestalten - ohne dass man dafür gleich in einer politischen Funktion sein muss. Viele junge Menschen interessieren sich verstärkt für Politik – aber dieses Interesse kommt in der (Partei-)Politik oft nicht an. Woran liegt das, warum ist das ein Problem, und wie kann es angegangen werden? Das ist ein Kommunikationsproblem – von beiden Seiten. Gerade die Bewegung Fridays For Future, aber auch die Gegenmobilisierung zu den geplanten Uploadfiltern in der Debatte um die Urheberschutzreform zeigen, dass ein verstärktes Bewusstsein in unserer Generation erwacht, dass (Europäische) Politik einen enormen Einfluss hat auf die Frage: wie wird unsere Zukunft gestaltet? Ein gutes Zeichen ist, das sich die jungen Protestbewegungen vor die Parlamente und Ministerien bewegen. Also ein großes Bewusstsein dafür herrscht, das dort diese Entscheidungen getroffen werden. Ich appelliere immer, den Kontakt zur (Partei)politik zu suchen, wenn man möchte, dass das Anliegen gehört wird. Druck machen - dort, wo die Entscheidungen getroffen werden. Gleichzeitig muss auch die Politik viel offener auf solche Jugendbewegungen zugehen, zuhören und das Anliegen ernst nehmen. Ansonsten bleibt die Lebensrealität junger Menschen im politischen Prozess ungehört. Welche Tipps hättest du für junge Menschen, die sich politisch engagieren möchten, aber nicht wissen wie oder wo sie anfangen sollen? Überleg dir, welche Themen dir am Herzen liegen und womit du dich einbringen möchtest. Man ist nie zu 100% einer Meinung mit dem Programm einer Partei, aber das Spannende ist: Man kann dafür sorgen, dass sich Programme weiterentwickeln! Nutze diese Chance und suche dir Verbündete, die mit dir für Veränderung und deine Ideen streiten. Wenn du deinem 5 oder 10 Jahre jüngeren Ich einen Tipp geben könntest (in Bezug auf politisches Engagement) – was wäre das? Vielleicht wäre es genau das: Sei kreativ und sei mutig für Veränderung einzustehen! Auch wenn Leute, die deine Eltern oder Großeltern sein könnten dir sagen, dass dieses und jenes nicht geht, weil es schon immer so gemacht wurde - lass dich davon nicht unterbuttern, sondern nutze deine Stimme und zeige, dass es eben doch anders geht! Liebe Delara, vielen Dank für das spannende Interview und viel Erfolg für die Wahl am 26. Mai! &amp;nbsp; Und Du, liebe Leserin und lieber Leser? Bist Du startklar für die Europawahl am 26. Mai? Wenn du in Deutschland in deinem Heimatort im Wählerverzeichnis eingetragen bist, solltest Du Deine Wahlbenachrichtigung ganz normal per Post erhalten. Solltest du am 26. Mai verhindert sein, kannst Du eine Briefwahl beantragen. Falls Du (wie ich) nicht mehr in Deutschland gemeldet bist und im Ausland lebst, kannst Du Dich hier ins Wählerverzeichnis eintragen lassen und alle nötigen Unterlagen beantragen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pflichtlektüre 2018: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/das-millennial-manifest-von-bianca-jankovska/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pflichtlektüre 2018: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska" /><published>2018-11-18T20:09:24+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-18T20:09:24+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/das-millennial-manifest-von-bianca-jankovska</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/das-millennial-manifest-von-bianca-jankovska/">&lt;p&gt;Ich habe einen Zettel von der belgischen Post in meinem Brüssler Briefkasten. Obwohl ich mich nicht daran erinnern kann, etwas bestellt zu haben, marschiere ich zur Post, um mein Überraschungspaket abzuholen. Zu meiner Freude halte ich fünfzehn Minuten später &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Ddg4JR&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Das Millennial Manifest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; von Bianca Jankovska in den Händen; ich hatte es bereits vor Monaten ungeduldig vorbestellt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfektes Timing - denn ich packe gerade meine Tasche für einen Kurzurlaub über's lange Wochenende. Zwar bin ich bereits tief in einem anderen Roman versunken (&lt;em&gt;The Book Thief&lt;/em&gt; von Markus Zusak), aber Jankovskas ersten Buch nehme ich trotzdem - und verschlinge es in anderthalb Tagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schon seit Jahren lese ich &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groschenphilosophin.at/2017/01/schreiben-fuer-geld-pt-1-davon-zu-leben-aendert-alles/&quot;&gt;Bianca Jankovskas Texte&lt;/a&gt; sehr gerne, genauso wie &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/groschenphilosophin/&quot;&gt;ihre Instagram-Beiträge&lt;/a&gt;. Deshalb bin ich nicht überrascht, dass ihr Buch extrem gut geschrieben ist: Witzig, nahbar, persönlich und ehrlich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Für Euch gelesen und rezensiert: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska. Fazit: 5 Sterne&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Einer Generation aus der Seele gesprochen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Das Millennial Manifest&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span data-hook=&quot;review-body&quot;&gt; ist eine Sammlung von Essays, die sich so wunderbar passend aneinanderreihen, dass ich gar nicht anders kann, als gleich das nächste zu lesen. Und das nächste. Und das nächste. In den drei Teilen des Buches geht es jeweils um Dating und Liebe (&lt;em&gt;&quot;1. Kann das Liebe oder ist das weg?&quot;&lt;/em&gt;), um zunehmend prekäre Arbeitsbedingungen für junge Menschen (&lt;em&gt;&quot;2. Willkommen in der Ellbogengesellschaft&quot;&lt;/em&gt;) und um Selbstverwirklichung und Privatleben (&lt;em&gt;&quot;3. Namaste my Ass&quot;&lt;/em&gt;). So viele der Situationen, sprechen vermutlich nicht nur mir, sondern auch vielen anderen so-genannten Millennials (also jungen Menschen zwischen Mitte zwanzig und Anfang dreißig) aus der Seele: von Tinder-Knigge über den ganz normalen Social-Media-Wahnsinn bis hin zum Berufseinstieg. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span data-hook=&quot;review-body&quot;&gt;Was macht die &lt;/span&gt;permanente digitale Erreichbarkeit mit unserem Liebesleben? Was passiert mit unserem Lebensgefühl, wenn scheinbar jeder auf Instagram das perfekte Leben führt - nur man selbst nicht? Und was macht es mit uns, wenn auf dem Arbeitsmarkt jeder mit jedem konkurriert und alle ersetzbar scheinen (zumindest manchen Branchen)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ob Germanistik-student/in oder Krankenpfleger/in:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ist es okay, dass es &quot;normal&quot; geworden ist, dass immer mehr junge Menschen erst mal eine gewisse Zeit unter- oder gar ganz unbezahlt arbeiten müssen? Oder dass immer mehr junge Menschen es nicht schaffen auszuziehen obwohl sie einen Job haben, weil ihr Verdienst zu gering ist und die Mieten einfach zu hoch? Dass immer mehr junge Menschen immer länger &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jetzt.de/job/finanziell-abhaengig-von-den-eltern-trotz-job&quot;&gt;finanziell von ihren Eltern abhängig sind&lt;/a&gt;, bevor sie mit Ende zwanzig, Anfang dreißig finanziell endlich mal selbst auf eigenen Beinen stehen können - von Familiengründung mit Haus am Stadtrand mal abgesehen? Und was ist mit denen, deren Eltern ihnen finanziell nicht unter die Arme greifen können, selbst wenn sie es wollten?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Ist es okay, dass heute immer mehr junge Menschen trotz Top-Ausbildung und Vollzeit-Job finanziell nicht auf eigenen Beinen stehen können? &quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jankovska schreibt (und das habe ich auch schon häufig beobachtet): Die Tatsache, dass immer mehr Arbeitgeber prekäre Arbeitsverhältnisse &quot;mit einer 'tollen Atmosphäre' und 'viel Spielraum' legitimieren&quot; führt dazu, &quot;dass viele Plätze logischerweise nur von denen in Anspruch genommen werden können, die tatsächlich aus einem privilegierten Haushalt stammen und sich auf die [schlecht oder unterbezahlte] Arbeit stürzen können, statt sich darauf konzentrieren zu müssen, was abends auf dem Teller landet&quot;. Man lerne ja so viel in diesen Praktika sei das Argument: &quot;Das mag einerseits schon stimmen, andererseits fängt genau hier die Ungleichheit zwischen gesellschaftlichen Schichten zu greifen an. Wer wird die Chance bekommen, etwas zu lernen?&quot; (S. 127-128)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wer bekommt die besten (Berufs-)Chancen?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fakt ist: junge Menschen, haben es heute oftmals schwerer mit Berufseinstieg und Existenzgründung: &quot;Was an ökonomischem Kapital und Connections fehlt, muss später mit Bereitschaft - und wie man so gerne sagt: Motivation - wiedergutgemacht werden (S. 86)&quot;. Mit einer kleinen aber wichtigen Einschränkung: Motivation und harte Arbeit alleine reichen meistens nicht, um den Mangel an Geld und Beziehungen auszugleichen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und was ist eigentlich mit der Masse an #feel-good #Millennials, die uns von Instagram bis YouTube mit ihrem #entrepreneurial #lifestyle die Nase lang ziehen? Was ist mit den ganzen Blendern à la: &quot;Wie ich als um die Welt reise und als digitaler Nomade arbeite - und wie du das auch schaffst&quot;? Von wegen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kann wirklich jeder das werden was er möchte?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jankovska kritisiert in ihrem Buch, dass sich viel zu viele Menschen ihrer Privilegien nicht bewusst sind. Zu häufig wird so getan, als ob &quot;jeder das werden kann, was er möchte, wenn er oder sie nur fest genug daran glaubt. Und wenn man auf seinen Job oder sein Studium keinen Bock mehr hat, dann 'könne man ja schließlich auch etwas anderes tun'. Zumindest, wenn die Eltern hinterher für den neuen Lifestyle blechen.&quot; Das Problem in dieser Annahme liegt auf der Hand. Denn &quot;nicht jeder hat das Glück, schon von seinen Eltern die Grundfeste eines friedvollen Lebens in die Wiege gelegt zu bekommen: Geld zum Beispiel (S. 199-201)&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nun, das war schon immer so, nicht wahr? Schon immer gab es Ungerechtigkeiten und Ungleichheiten, schon immer hatten manche Menschen es leichter, und andere schwerer. Doch was hat sich innerhalb der letzten Generation/en verändert? Ist es die Politik im Allgemeinen? Ist es ein dysfunktionaler Kapitalismus? Ist es die Wirtschaftskrise? Oder ist es vielleicht alles davon? &quot;Die Wirtschaftskrise kannten wir [während der Schulzeit] aus den Zeitungen. Im BWL-Unterricht führten wir Tagebuch darüber, als ob es sich dabei um eine lustige Geschichte und nicht das Dahinbröckeln unserer Zukunft handelte (S. 80)&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Junge Menschen haben es heute schwerer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ihrem Buch bringt Jankovska mit Biss und Humor ein Phänomen auf den Punkt, dass eben leider gar nicht zum Lachen ist: Junge Menschen haben es heute oftmals - trotz hohem (Aus-)Bildungsgrad - deutlich schwerer, finanziell klarzukommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bianca Jankovska liefert die persönlichen Storys, Aktivist &lt;a href=&quot;https://editionf.com/wolfgang-gruendinger-interview-alte-saecke-politik&quot;&gt;Wolfgang Gründinger liefert die Zahlen&lt;/a&gt;: „Diese Lohnlücke zwischen Jung und Alt gibt es tatsächlich, und sie driftet immer weiter auseinander. Vor vierzig Jahren erhielten junge Arbeitnehmerinnen und Arbeitnehmer noch etwa 12 Prozent weniger Lohn als ältere, heute sind es schon knapp 25 Prozent. Auch das Vermögen konzentriert sich immer stärker bei den Alten: Damals besaßen die Älteren pro Haushalt noch zweimal mehr als die Jungen, heute schon viermal mehr. Niedriglöhne und unsichere Beschäftigungsverhältnisse betreffen vor allem die Jungen, die teilweise sogar vom Mindestlohn ausgenommen sind. Wer nicht gerade in ein wohlhabendes Elternhaus geboren wurde, hat es schwerer als früher, sich eine Existenz aufzubauen.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Lohnlücke zwischen Jung und Alt hat sich in den letzten 40 Jahren verdoppelt: von 12% auf 25%. Zudem: Niedriglöhne und unsichere Verträge treffen vor allem junge Menschen.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sie haben weniger Geld und weniger Zeit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait a minute. der Lohnunterschied hat sich verdoppelt? Das ist nicht alles: Das Institut der deutschen Wirtschaft in Köln hat in einer Studie herausgefunden, dass ältere Altersgruppen innerhalb der von 25 Jahre &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iwkoeln.de/presse/pressemitteilungen/beitrag/lebensverhaeltnisse-aeltere-stehen-besser-da-339199.html&quot;&gt;einen fast drei mal so hohen Lohnanstieg hatten&lt;/a&gt;, als jüngere. Drei Mal so hoch. Selbstfindung, Avocado-Toast und Weltreise? Die wenigsten können sich das leisten; das ist etwas, was &quot;die anderen&quot; auf Instagram machen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Millennials: Selbstfindung, Avocado-Toast und Weltreise? Von wegen. Das können sich nur 'die anderen' auf Instagram leisten.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darüber gesprochen wird laut Jankovska trotzdem nicht genug - oder nicht laut genug, nicht oft genug, nicht organisiert genug. Im Kontext der geplanten Einführung des 12-Stundentags in Österreich zitiert Jankovska die Autorin und Aktivistin Jelena Gučanin: &quot;Es soll sogar Menschen geben, die arbeiten, um über die Runden zu kommen. Die sich in die Krankheit arbeiten, um ihren Job zu behalten. Und auch jene, die nicht arbeiten, weil es zu wenige Jobs gibt. Und alle von ihnen haben ein Leben, ein soziales Umfeld, private Verpflichtungen, Hobbys und, man stelle sich vor: auch den Wunsch, mehr Freizeit zu haben. Also verwechselt hier nichts: Arbeitszeit wird verlängert. Arbeiterinnenrechte werden beschnitten. Get your facts straight. And organize.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dass viele junge Menschen bei dem Versuch, sich einigermaßen eine Existenz aufzubauen, nicht besonders viel Energie für aktives politisches Engagement übrig bleibt, ist nachvollziehbar. Und wer es doch versuchen will, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonworth.eu/it-did-not-work-to-get-onto-the-ep-list-for-the-greens-some-lessons/&quot;&gt;hat es alles andere als leicht&lt;/a&gt; und braucht nicht nur ein dickes Fell, sondern auch viel Zeit, Geduld und vor allem Geld. Und das können sich die meisten ohne Unterstützung von außen beim besten Willen nicht leisten, sagt auch die kürzlich neu-gewählte 29-jährige &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Ocasio2018/status/1060588813582585858&quot;&gt;US-Kongressabgeordnete Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Es ist leicht, &quot;unsere Generation&quot; als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nun, nicht jeder kann und möchte sich ein politisches Amt erkämpfen. Aber ein allererster Schritt ist doch mal, Dinge die schief laufen anzusprechen und im Kleinen aktiv zu werden. So kann man erst mal ein breiteres Bewusstsein dafür schaffen, dass es so nicht weitergehen kann - oder dass man es zumindest ein bisschen besser machen könnte. Und nur weil man die perfekt ausgearbeiteten Lösungen selbst nicht in petto hat, sollte es einen nicht davon abhalten, vorhandene Probleme und mögliche Lösungen mit anderen zu diskutieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doch bereits hier liegt das erste Problem. Wir erinnern uns: immer mehr junge Menschen haben mit prekären Arbeitsverhältnissen und finanziellen Sorgen zu kämpfen. Unangenehm auffallen? Nee, lass mal lieber, ich habe größere Sorgen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&quot;Ich wünsche mir, mehr Menschen würden den Mund aufmachen&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bianca Jankovska erzählt: seitdem sie selbst unbequeme Wahrheiten, zum Beispiel in der Arbeitswelt, konsequent und unmissverständlich anspricht, wird sie oft von Familie und Freunden gewarnt: &quot;Bist du sicher, dass du dir damit nicht selbst eine Grube gräbst?&quot;, &quot;Wer will denn jemanden einstellen, der so radikale Äußerungen von sich gibt - und das auch noch öffentlich?&quot; Jankovka wünscht sich, dass mehr Menschen den Mund aufmachen. Denn wenn sie sich &quot;kollektiv gegen Missstände - und sei es nur im Kleinen, im eigenen Betrieb - zusammentun würden, dann hätte das aufschreiende Individuum weniger zu befürchten. Ganz einfach, weil alle am Widerstand beteiligt wären (S. 165).&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Buch-Rezension: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska. 'Es ist leicht, unsere Generation als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen'.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Es ist leicht, 'unsere Generation' - als ob es sich dabei um eine homogene Masse handeln würde - als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen, wenn das kleinste Fehlverhalten zum Branchenausschluss oder zur Kündigung führt, wenn man für ehrliche Worte auf einer imaginären roten Liste landet, die einem bis zum Wechsel der Vorstandsebene Türen verschließt (S. 154).&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Was bedeutet es eigentlich, heute &quot;politisch&quot; zu sein?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Frage, die mir nach dem Buch am klebrigsten im Kopf stecken bleibt ist: Was bedeutet es denn heutzutage eigentlich, politisch zu sein? Muss man dafür Parteimitglied sein und sich in zähen Ortsvereinssitzungen regelmäßig den Hintern plattsitzen? Ain't nobody got time for that! Politisches Engagement ist nicht besonders sexy, weil es eben mit jenen drögen Parteien in Verbindung gebracht wird, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stern.de/neon/wilde-welt/politik/warum-junge-menschen-sich-von-der-politik-nicht-repraesentiert-fuehlen-8372348.html&quot;&gt;von denen sich niemand repräsentiert fühlt&lt;/a&gt; und mit denen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/politik-warum-jugendliche-sich-nicht-an-parteien-binden-a-1127968.html&quot;&gt;niemand etwas zu tun haben will&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Was bedeutet es eigentlich, heute 'politisch' zu sein? Die Frage aller Fragen.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dennoch: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shell.de/ueber-uns/die-shell-jugendstudie/multimediale-inhalte/_jcr_content/par/expandablelist_643445253/expandablesection.stream/1456210165334/d0f5d09f09c6142df03cc804f0fb389c2d39e167115aa86c57276d240cca4f5f/flyer-zur-shell-jugendstudie-2015-auf-deutsch.pdf&quot;&gt;eine Jugend-Studie von 2015&lt;/a&gt; zeigt, dass junge Menschen sich heutzutage viel stärker für Politik und Aktivismus interessieren als vorherige Generationen. Denn Klimawandel, soziale Ungerechtigkeit, Bildungspolitik und Arbeitnehmerinnenschutz betrifft am Ende eben doch alle. Aber: die etablierten politischen &lt;span class=&quot;highlight selected&quot;&gt;Partei&lt;/span&gt;en profitieren von diesem neu entfachten Interesse nicht, denn das Vertrauen junger Menschen in diese Parteien ist verschwindend gering. Die Politikverdrossenheit bleibt hoch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Junge Menschen interessieren sich heute mehr für Politik als frühere Generationen. Doch politische Parteien profitieren hiervon nicht. Die Politikverdrossenheit bleibt hoch.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Welche Möglichkeiten etwas zu bewegen haben junge Menschen denn?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fluter.de/gewerkschaften-brauchen-junge-mitglieder&quot;&gt;Einer Gewerkschaft beitreten?&lt;/a&gt; Auch nicht gerade beliebt oder verbreitet. Jankovska schreibt: &quot;Zeit, zur Arbeiterkammer zu gehen und sich [über schlechte oder prekäre] Arbeitsbedingen zu beschweren, bleibt bei einer vollgepackten Woche auch nicht. 2:0 für den Kapitalismus (S. 109).&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dabei wären gerade in dieser neuen, modernen Arbeitswelt neue Arten von Kontrollmechanismen und Arbeitnehmerschutz angemessen, oder nicht? Anekdotisch spricht Jankovska ein Beispiel an: firmeninterne Whatsapp-Gruppen. Diese sind in der Theorie ein schneller und direkter Kommunikationskanal zwischen Mitarbeitern. In der Praxis sind sie jedoch im besten Fall nervig, und können im schlimmsten Fall hochgradig schädlich für die mentale Gesundheit von Mitarbeitern sein - nämlich wenn persönliche Grenzen dauerhaft und unreguliert überschritten werden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Die Schwelle, nach Feierabend in ein Chatfenster 'Morgen spontanes Meeting um 7:30' zu tippen, ist definitiv niedriger, als um 21 Uhr den Mitarbeiter anzurufen und ihm zu sagen, dass er eine Stunde früher im Büro sein muss.&quot; Das Problem: &quot;die ungeschriebenen Regeln einer Firmen-Whatsapp-Gruppe macht nicht der Betriebsrat - sondern der Chef (S. 140)&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fazit: Das Millennial Manifest ist unterhaltsam und regt hochgradig zum Denken an&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Für mich ist Bianca Jankovskas Buch nicht nur unterhaltsam, gut geschrieben und den-Nagel-auf-den-Kopf-treffend. Es möchte dazu ermutigen, die Missstände um uns herum öfter mal anzusprechen, anstatt die Dinge einfach so hinzunehmen und mit einem &quot;Das gehört eben dazu&quot; abzutun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deshalb ist das Millennial Manifest für mich auch politisch und regt zum Nachdenken an - und zum Träumen. Ja, wie wäre es denn, wenn wir zum Beispiel neue Betriebsräte gründen würden? Oder für Arbeitsbedingungen kämpfen, die an heutige Bedingungen angepasst sind? Wie wäre es denn, eine 20-Stunden-Woche für alle einzuführen, oder einen besseren Mindestlohn?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klar, das können wir eh vergessen, denn wie soll man das denn umsetzen? Unsere Generation ist politisch ja auch nicht gerade bestens repräsentiert: &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/millennials-and-politics-terry-reintke/&quot;&gt;Zum Beispiel&lt;/a&gt; sind nur 11% der Abgeordneten im europäischen Parlament unter 40 Jahre alt, und weniger als 2% sind gar unter 30. Im Deutschen Bundestag sieht es nicht anders aus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Wer vertritt eigentlich junge Menschen politisch? Nur 11% der Parlamentarier in Europa sind unter 40 Jahre alt, weniger als 2% sind gar unter 30.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und trotzdem. &quot;Was uns jetzt übrig bleibt: Wir können entweder träumen. Oder im Kleinen tätig werden (S. 89).&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was das für den einzelnen bedeutet, muss jeder für sich herausfinden, aber als allererstes solltet Ihr vor allem: &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2Ddg4JR&quot;&gt;dieses Buch kaufen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">Ich habe einen Zettel von der belgischen Post in meinem Brüssler Briefkasten. Obwohl ich mich nicht daran erinnern kann, etwas bestellt zu haben, marschiere ich zur Post, um mein Überraschungspaket abzuholen. Zu meiner Freude halte ich fünfzehn Minuten später Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska in den Händen; ich hatte es bereits vor Monaten ungeduldig vorbestellt. Perfektes Timing - denn ich packe gerade meine Tasche für einen Kurzurlaub über's lange Wochenende. Zwar bin ich bereits tief in einem anderen Roman versunken (The Book Thief von Markus Zusak), aber Jankovskas ersten Buch nehme ich trotzdem - und verschlinge es in anderthalb Tagen. Schon seit Jahren lese ich Bianca Jankovskas Texte sehr gerne, genauso wie ihre Instagram-Beiträge. Deshalb bin ich nicht überrascht, dass ihr Buch extrem gut geschrieben ist: Witzig, nahbar, persönlich und ehrlich. [bctt tweet=&quot;Für Euch gelesen und rezensiert: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska. Fazit: 5 Sterne&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Einer Generation aus der Seele gesprochen Das Millennial Manifest ist eine Sammlung von Essays, die sich so wunderbar passend aneinanderreihen, dass ich gar nicht anders kann, als gleich das nächste zu lesen. Und das nächste. Und das nächste. In den drei Teilen des Buches geht es jeweils um Dating und Liebe (&quot;1. Kann das Liebe oder ist das weg?&quot;), um zunehmend prekäre Arbeitsbedingungen für junge Menschen (&quot;2. Willkommen in der Ellbogengesellschaft&quot;) und um Selbstverwirklichung und Privatleben (&quot;3. Namaste my Ass&quot;). So viele der Situationen, sprechen vermutlich nicht nur mir, sondern auch vielen anderen so-genannten Millennials (also jungen Menschen zwischen Mitte zwanzig und Anfang dreißig) aus der Seele: von Tinder-Knigge über den ganz normalen Social-Media-Wahnsinn bis hin zum Berufseinstieg. Was macht die permanente digitale Erreichbarkeit mit unserem Liebesleben? Was passiert mit unserem Lebensgefühl, wenn scheinbar jeder auf Instagram das perfekte Leben führt - nur man selbst nicht? Und was macht es mit uns, wenn auf dem Arbeitsmarkt jeder mit jedem konkurriert und alle ersetzbar scheinen (zumindest manchen Branchen)? Ob Germanistik-student/in oder Krankenpfleger/in: Ist es okay, dass es &quot;normal&quot; geworden ist, dass immer mehr junge Menschen erst mal eine gewisse Zeit unter- oder gar ganz unbezahlt arbeiten müssen? Oder dass immer mehr junge Menschen es nicht schaffen auszuziehen obwohl sie einen Job haben, weil ihr Verdienst zu gering ist und die Mieten einfach zu hoch? Dass immer mehr junge Menschen immer länger finanziell von ihren Eltern abhängig sind, bevor sie mit Ende zwanzig, Anfang dreißig finanziell endlich mal selbst auf eigenen Beinen stehen können - von Familiengründung mit Haus am Stadtrand mal abgesehen? Und was ist mit denen, deren Eltern ihnen finanziell nicht unter die Arme greifen können, selbst wenn sie es wollten? [bctt tweet=&quot;Ist es okay, dass heute immer mehr junge Menschen trotz Top-Ausbildung und Vollzeit-Job finanziell nicht auf eigenen Beinen stehen können? &quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Jankovska schreibt (und das habe ich auch schon häufig beobachtet): Die Tatsache, dass immer mehr Arbeitgeber prekäre Arbeitsverhältnisse &quot;mit einer 'tollen Atmosphäre' und 'viel Spielraum' legitimieren&quot; führt dazu, &quot;dass viele Plätze logischerweise nur von denen in Anspruch genommen werden können, die tatsächlich aus einem privilegierten Haushalt stammen und sich auf die [schlecht oder unterbezahlte] Arbeit stürzen können, statt sich darauf konzentrieren zu müssen, was abends auf dem Teller landet&quot;. Man lerne ja so viel in diesen Praktika sei das Argument: &quot;Das mag einerseits schon stimmen, andererseits fängt genau hier die Ungleichheit zwischen gesellschaftlichen Schichten zu greifen an. Wer wird die Chance bekommen, etwas zu lernen?&quot; (S. 127-128) Wer bekommt die besten (Berufs-)Chancen? Fakt ist: junge Menschen, haben es heute oftmals schwerer mit Berufseinstieg und Existenzgründung: &quot;Was an ökonomischem Kapital und Connections fehlt, muss später mit Bereitschaft - und wie man so gerne sagt: Motivation - wiedergutgemacht werden (S. 86)&quot;. Mit einer kleinen aber wichtigen Einschränkung: Motivation und harte Arbeit alleine reichen meistens nicht, um den Mangel an Geld und Beziehungen auszugleichen. Und was ist eigentlich mit der Masse an #feel-good #Millennials, die uns von Instagram bis YouTube mit ihrem #entrepreneurial #lifestyle die Nase lang ziehen? Was ist mit den ganzen Blendern à la: &quot;Wie ich als um die Welt reise und als digitaler Nomade arbeite - und wie du das auch schaffst&quot;? Von wegen. Kann wirklich jeder das werden was er möchte? Jankovska kritisiert in ihrem Buch, dass sich viel zu viele Menschen ihrer Privilegien nicht bewusst sind. Zu häufig wird so getan, als ob &quot;jeder das werden kann, was er möchte, wenn er oder sie nur fest genug daran glaubt. Und wenn man auf seinen Job oder sein Studium keinen Bock mehr hat, dann 'könne man ja schließlich auch etwas anderes tun'. Zumindest, wenn die Eltern hinterher für den neuen Lifestyle blechen.&quot; Das Problem in dieser Annahme liegt auf der Hand. Denn &quot;nicht jeder hat das Glück, schon von seinen Eltern die Grundfeste eines friedvollen Lebens in die Wiege gelegt zu bekommen: Geld zum Beispiel (S. 199-201)&quot;. Nun, das war schon immer so, nicht wahr? Schon immer gab es Ungerechtigkeiten und Ungleichheiten, schon immer hatten manche Menschen es leichter, und andere schwerer. Doch was hat sich innerhalb der letzten Generation/en verändert? Ist es die Politik im Allgemeinen? Ist es ein dysfunktionaler Kapitalismus? Ist es die Wirtschaftskrise? Oder ist es vielleicht alles davon? &quot;Die Wirtschaftskrise kannten wir [während der Schulzeit] aus den Zeitungen. Im BWL-Unterricht führten wir Tagebuch darüber, als ob es sich dabei um eine lustige Geschichte und nicht das Dahinbröckeln unserer Zukunft handelte (S. 80)&quot;. Junge Menschen haben es heute schwerer In ihrem Buch bringt Jankovska mit Biss und Humor ein Phänomen auf den Punkt, dass eben leider gar nicht zum Lachen ist: Junge Menschen haben es heute oftmals - trotz hohem (Aus-)Bildungsgrad - deutlich schwerer, finanziell klarzukommen. Bianca Jankovska liefert die persönlichen Storys, Aktivist Wolfgang Gründinger liefert die Zahlen: „Diese Lohnlücke zwischen Jung und Alt gibt es tatsächlich, und sie driftet immer weiter auseinander. Vor vierzig Jahren erhielten junge Arbeitnehmerinnen und Arbeitnehmer noch etwa 12 Prozent weniger Lohn als ältere, heute sind es schon knapp 25 Prozent. Auch das Vermögen konzentriert sich immer stärker bei den Alten: Damals besaßen die Älteren pro Haushalt noch zweimal mehr als die Jungen, heute schon viermal mehr. Niedriglöhne und unsichere Beschäftigungsverhältnisse betreffen vor allem die Jungen, die teilweise sogar vom Mindestlohn ausgenommen sind. Wer nicht gerade in ein wohlhabendes Elternhaus geboren wurde, hat es schwerer als früher, sich eine Existenz aufzubauen.“ [bctt tweet=&quot;Lohnlücke zwischen Jung und Alt hat sich in den letzten 40 Jahren verdoppelt: von 12% auf 25%. Zudem: Niedriglöhne und unsichere Verträge treffen vor allem junge Menschen.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Sie haben weniger Geld und weniger Zeit Wait a minute. der Lohnunterschied hat sich verdoppelt? Das ist nicht alles: Das Institut der deutschen Wirtschaft in Köln hat in einer Studie herausgefunden, dass ältere Altersgruppen innerhalb der von 25 Jahre einen fast drei mal so hohen Lohnanstieg hatten, als jüngere. Drei Mal so hoch. Selbstfindung, Avocado-Toast und Weltreise? Die wenigsten können sich das leisten; das ist etwas, was &quot;die anderen&quot; auf Instagram machen. [bctt tweet=&quot;Millennials: Selbstfindung, Avocado-Toast und Weltreise? Von wegen. Das können sich nur 'die anderen' auf Instagram leisten.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Darüber gesprochen wird laut Jankovska trotzdem nicht genug - oder nicht laut genug, nicht oft genug, nicht organisiert genug. Im Kontext der geplanten Einführung des 12-Stundentags in Österreich zitiert Jankovska die Autorin und Aktivistin Jelena Gučanin: &quot;Es soll sogar Menschen geben, die arbeiten, um über die Runden zu kommen. Die sich in die Krankheit arbeiten, um ihren Job zu behalten. Und auch jene, die nicht arbeiten, weil es zu wenige Jobs gibt. Und alle von ihnen haben ein Leben, ein soziales Umfeld, private Verpflichtungen, Hobbys und, man stelle sich vor: auch den Wunsch, mehr Freizeit zu haben. Also verwechselt hier nichts: Arbeitszeit wird verlängert. Arbeiterinnenrechte werden beschnitten. Get your facts straight. And organize.&quot; Dass viele junge Menschen bei dem Versuch, sich einigermaßen eine Existenz aufzubauen, nicht besonders viel Energie für aktives politisches Engagement übrig bleibt, ist nachvollziehbar. Und wer es doch versuchen will, hat es alles andere als leicht und braucht nicht nur ein dickes Fell, sondern auch viel Zeit, Geduld und vor allem Geld. Und das können sich die meisten ohne Unterstützung von außen beim besten Willen nicht leisten, sagt auch die kürzlich neu-gewählte 29-jährige US-Kongressabgeordnete Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez. Es ist leicht, &quot;unsere Generation&quot; als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen Nun, nicht jeder kann und möchte sich ein politisches Amt erkämpfen. Aber ein allererster Schritt ist doch mal, Dinge die schief laufen anzusprechen und im Kleinen aktiv zu werden. So kann man erst mal ein breiteres Bewusstsein dafür schaffen, dass es so nicht weitergehen kann - oder dass man es zumindest ein bisschen besser machen könnte. Und nur weil man die perfekt ausgearbeiteten Lösungen selbst nicht in petto hat, sollte es einen nicht davon abhalten, vorhandene Probleme und mögliche Lösungen mit anderen zu diskutieren. Doch bereits hier liegt das erste Problem. Wir erinnern uns: immer mehr junge Menschen haben mit prekären Arbeitsverhältnissen und finanziellen Sorgen zu kämpfen. Unangenehm auffallen? Nee, lass mal lieber, ich habe größere Sorgen. &quot;Ich wünsche mir, mehr Menschen würden den Mund aufmachen&quot; Bianca Jankovska erzählt: seitdem sie selbst unbequeme Wahrheiten, zum Beispiel in der Arbeitswelt, konsequent und unmissverständlich anspricht, wird sie oft von Familie und Freunden gewarnt: &quot;Bist du sicher, dass du dir damit nicht selbst eine Grube gräbst?&quot;, &quot;Wer will denn jemanden einstellen, der so radikale Äußerungen von sich gibt - und das auch noch öffentlich?&quot; Jankovka wünscht sich, dass mehr Menschen den Mund aufmachen. Denn wenn sie sich &quot;kollektiv gegen Missstände - und sei es nur im Kleinen, im eigenen Betrieb - zusammentun würden, dann hätte das aufschreiende Individuum weniger zu befürchten. Ganz einfach, weil alle am Widerstand beteiligt wären (S. 165).&quot; [bctt tweet=&quot;Buch-Rezension: Das Millennial Manifest von Bianca Jankovska. 'Es ist leicht, unsere Generation als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen'.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] &quot;Es ist leicht, 'unsere Generation' - als ob es sich dabei um eine homogene Masse handeln würde - als unpolitisch zu bezeichnen, wenn das kleinste Fehlverhalten zum Branchenausschluss oder zur Kündigung führt, wenn man für ehrliche Worte auf einer imaginären roten Liste landet, die einem bis zum Wechsel der Vorstandsebene Türen verschließt (S. 154).&quot; Was bedeutet es eigentlich, heute &quot;politisch&quot; zu sein? Die Frage, die mir nach dem Buch am klebrigsten im Kopf stecken bleibt ist: Was bedeutet es denn heutzutage eigentlich, politisch zu sein? Muss man dafür Parteimitglied sein und sich in zähen Ortsvereinssitzungen regelmäßig den Hintern plattsitzen? Ain't nobody got time for that! Politisches Engagement ist nicht besonders sexy, weil es eben mit jenen drögen Parteien in Verbindung gebracht wird, von denen sich niemand repräsentiert fühlt und mit denen niemand etwas zu tun haben will. [bctt tweet=&quot;Was bedeutet es eigentlich, heute 'politisch' zu sein? Die Frage aller Fragen.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Dennoch: eine Jugend-Studie von 2015 zeigt, dass junge Menschen sich heutzutage viel stärker für Politik und Aktivismus interessieren als vorherige Generationen. Denn Klimawandel, soziale Ungerechtigkeit, Bildungspolitik und Arbeitnehmerinnenschutz betrifft am Ende eben doch alle. Aber: die etablierten politischen Parteien profitieren von diesem neu entfachten Interesse nicht, denn das Vertrauen junger Menschen in diese Parteien ist verschwindend gering. Die Politikverdrossenheit bleibt hoch. [bctt tweet=&quot;Junge Menschen interessieren sich heute mehr für Politik als frühere Generationen. Doch politische Parteien profitieren hiervon nicht. Die Politikverdrossenheit bleibt hoch.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Welche Möglichkeiten etwas zu bewegen haben junge Menschen denn? Einer Gewerkschaft beitreten? Auch nicht gerade beliebt oder verbreitet. Jankovska schreibt: &quot;Zeit, zur Arbeiterkammer zu gehen und sich [über schlechte oder prekäre] Arbeitsbedingen zu beschweren, bleibt bei einer vollgepackten Woche auch nicht. 2:0 für den Kapitalismus (S. 109).&quot; Dabei wären gerade in dieser neuen, modernen Arbeitswelt neue Arten von Kontrollmechanismen und Arbeitnehmerschutz angemessen, oder nicht? Anekdotisch spricht Jankovska ein Beispiel an: firmeninterne Whatsapp-Gruppen. Diese sind in der Theorie ein schneller und direkter Kommunikationskanal zwischen Mitarbeitern. In der Praxis sind sie jedoch im besten Fall nervig, und können im schlimmsten Fall hochgradig schädlich für die mentale Gesundheit von Mitarbeitern sein - nämlich wenn persönliche Grenzen dauerhaft und unreguliert überschritten werden. &quot;Die Schwelle, nach Feierabend in ein Chatfenster 'Morgen spontanes Meeting um 7:30' zu tippen, ist definitiv niedriger, als um 21 Uhr den Mitarbeiter anzurufen und ihm zu sagen, dass er eine Stunde früher im Büro sein muss.&quot; Das Problem: &quot;die ungeschriebenen Regeln einer Firmen-Whatsapp-Gruppe macht nicht der Betriebsrat - sondern der Chef (S. 140)&quot;. Fazit: Das Millennial Manifest ist unterhaltsam und regt hochgradig zum Denken an Für mich ist Bianca Jankovskas Buch nicht nur unterhaltsam, gut geschrieben und den-Nagel-auf-den-Kopf-treffend. Es möchte dazu ermutigen, die Missstände um uns herum öfter mal anzusprechen, anstatt die Dinge einfach so hinzunehmen und mit einem &quot;Das gehört eben dazu&quot; abzutun. Deshalb ist das Millennial Manifest für mich auch politisch und regt zum Nachdenken an - und zum Träumen. Ja, wie wäre es denn, wenn wir zum Beispiel neue Betriebsräte gründen würden? Oder für Arbeitsbedingungen kämpfen, die an heutige Bedingungen angepasst sind? Wie wäre es denn, eine 20-Stunden-Woche für alle einzuführen, oder einen besseren Mindestlohn? Klar, das können wir eh vergessen, denn wie soll man das denn umsetzen? Unsere Generation ist politisch ja auch nicht gerade bestens repräsentiert: Zum Beispiel sind nur 11% der Abgeordneten im europäischen Parlament unter 40 Jahre alt, und weniger als 2% sind gar unter 30. Im Deutschen Bundestag sieht es nicht anders aus. [bctt tweet=&quot;Wer vertritt eigentlich junge Menschen politisch? Nur 11% der Parlamentarier in Europa sind unter 40 Jahre alt, weniger als 2% sind gar unter 30.&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] Und trotzdem. &quot;Was uns jetzt übrig bleibt: Wir können entweder träumen. Oder im Kleinen tätig werden (S. 89).&quot; Was das für den einzelnen bedeutet, muss jeder für sich herausfinden, aber als allererstes solltet Ihr vor allem: dieses Buch kaufen.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“It is scary to put yourself out there. But it is even scarier to be passive.”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/it-is-scary-to-put-yourself-out-there-but-it-is-even-scarier-to-be-passive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;It is scary to put yourself out there. But it is even scarier to be passive.&quot;" /><published>2018-07-13T07:44:24+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-13T07:44:24+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/it-is-scary-to-put-yourself-out-there-but-it-is-even-scarier-to-be-passive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/it-is-scary-to-put-yourself-out-there-but-it-is-even-scarier-to-be-passive/">&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure to speak to Ciara O'Riordan about young people, politics and tech. Ciara works for Ecanvasser in Ireland - an app that helps political candidates organise their campaign by connecting the offline- with the online world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciara is a professional in digital marketing and political campaigning, and I wanted to hear her take on why &quot;Millennials&quot; aren't as prominent in the political landscape as they should be. You can’t argue with the numbers: People under 30 make up &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Being_young_in_Europe_today_-_demographic_trends&quot;&gt;17% of the population&lt;/a&gt; (that excludes children); yet, they provide less than &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.ipu.org/pdf/publications/youthrep-e.pdf&quot;&gt;2% of all members of parliament&lt;/a&gt;, and rarely hold high political office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to know from Ciara: What are the problems young people encounter when getting politically active and how can more young people get a seat at the table?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ciara, there's a common misconception that young people are simply not interested in politics. Do you think this is true?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a really easy statement to accept and not question too much, but I don’t agree. What needs to be understood is that there is a difference between party politics and politics. Yes, it is true that young people are not hugely involved with party politics, though I do think there is significant underreporting taking place. We see young people highly active online about a range of policy issues and structural reform on a daily basis. But, in the broader area of politics that encompasses issues, activism and civic engagement, I do think young people are highly engaged. It is just not easy to quantify the level of engagement in terms of membership numbers and so on, because that is not the way it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people are much more tuned in nowadays that we give ourselves credit for. We saw it here in Ireland in 2015, when the marriage equality referendum was taking place. The backbone of the equality side was a young demographic - they were the most vocal, the most unabashed. That’s being pretty interested in politics I would say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you get down to it, politics is nothing more than people operating with each other, connecting and trying to represent. There isn’t much about that that young people can’t relate to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And yet, party memberships are steadily declining. Why? Are political parties dead? Can they be revived?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is something that I find particularly interesting to talk about and dissect. Young people definitely love an issue-based campaign. Anything that we can see a solution for or something that we cause an impact on, we’ll be onboard with. Like the marriage equality referendum of 2015 I referred to, and more recently the referendum on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighth_Amendment_of_the_Constitution_of_Ireland&quot;&gt;8th amendment&lt;/a&gt;, which saw loads of people become politically engaged. This weirdly doesn’t seem to translate to party politics, nor to local and general elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think party membership is affected by cynicism. It’s very hard to make a dent in the long established political wheel. Instead, the temptation would be to run as an independent candidate or even form your own party. We saw this case with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renua&quot;&gt;Renua&lt;/a&gt; in the last Irish General Election. But they were wiped out across the board, as the electorate didn’t see a past, present or future for them. This happens in many countries across Europe too, as we constantly see new parties rise and fall virtually overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it disheartening trying to get into politics? Most definitely. But should people just give up? Absolutely not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why do you think it is important for young people to take an interest in politics, and more importantly, to take action?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty straight forward for me. Politics impacts nearly all aspects of our lives. It’s not something a lot of us see, until we start working or maybe get to college. But it is so important to be tuned in to politics and the repercussions of it. Politics forms the frame of our lives, and the earlier people get involved, the better they will be able to impact on that framing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m certainly not advocating that everyone should be affiliated with party politics or should hold strong opinions on policy or anything but...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we need to help people understand that politics and governments' decisions have big impacts on everyone in society. It’s scary to me at times to see how passive we can be about this. Is it a lack of understanding or is it years of feeling wronged by big party politics? Maybe a mixture of both even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Young people today, so-called Millennials, are under-represented in political decision making. Why do you think this is the case, and what can be done to fix it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate to use the dreaded Q word but are quotas the answer? Should each party or elected committee have a person who is aged between 18-25 or 20-30? The challenge is that we need more young people running, for more young people to be elected. Most things don’t require complex solutions but only pretty simple ones. I think we should consider offering funding and scholarships for aspiring young politicians. Giving them support so they can succeed, instead of making it easier for them to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Is the future of politics happening online? What is the importance of offline people-to-people relationships?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Campaign strategist &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumeliegey&quot;&gt;Guillaume Liegey&lt;/a&gt; talks about Data/Tech/Human to describe the way in which offline face-to-face contact in the community or on the doorsteps fits into the data infrastructure of political organisations. They are not separate - they are connected and supportive of each other. In the same way, if you were to conduct all of your political interactions exclusively online, you would miss whole sections of society that do not interact there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, nothing really beats face-to-face interaction. I love online platforms like Twitter and Instagram, but there is always going to be something lacking. Real life conversations can’t be as easily misconstrued as online ones. How many times a day do we see tone being taken up incorrectly online, no matter how many emojis you use!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will always be a place online for politics and the discussion surrounding it, but ultimately the action we want to see implemented off the back of it will happen offline. It’s always more effort to do things away from a keyboard. but the results are always a little bit better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you engage politically? How did you get started?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so many different ways to be involved in politics. I always admire people who operate on the frontline and the activists who drive the movements that are close to their own hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would see myself as being very civically minded, and I enjoy working on a local basis in my own community at home. No matter the organisation - grassroots is a fundamental in being successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Ecanvasser, we see ourselves as being architects of democracy. Working as technicians in the political software sector is a great place to be at the moment, because you get to be fully immersed in the campaign cycle. Working with new candidates as they begin their campaigns means you can learn so much and you can also turn all these learnings into useful resources to push out to the next generation of candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is your motivation for supporting &quot;political beginners&quot; with free resources and advice? Where did you gain that expertise?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company mission at Ecanvasser is about allowing anyone to run for office. The barrier of entry being lowered is something we spoke about 4 years ago and still talk about everyday in the office. People need to understand that politics is collaborative. So why not share all the useful tips you have to help people reach their goals! That’s why our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecanvasser.com/campaignblueprint/&quot;&gt;Campaign Blueprint&lt;/a&gt; section is one of our most utilised sections on our website and also why we feel the need to constantly share videos on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbIn8wXeImvNctFdn96a-5w?pbjreload=10&quot;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything changes so quickly between election cycles, it’s important for us to always be evolving and trying to stay on trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is your #1 advice for young people who want to get politically involved, but don‘t know where and how to get started?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we - all of us, and maybe especially young people - don’t realise the value that we have, whether that is in a work context or in civil society. If you think you are going to be an addition somewhere instead of  subtraction, get involved! I think some young people really have that “fear factor” when it comes to putting themselves out there to be judged. We need to lose this and just go for it. It’s as simple as this: you have to start somewhere - so start by joining an issue group or organisation that you are passionate about. Think of politics as an apprenticeship for life, there is so much to learn and many avenues that you can explore. Consider an area that you want to impact and research groups in that area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thank you Ciara for this insightful conversation!&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">I had the pleasure to speak to Ciara O'Riordan about young people, politics and tech. Ciara works for Ecanvasser in Ireland - an app that helps political candidates organise their campaign by connecting the offline- with the online world. Ciara is a professional in digital marketing and political campaigning, and I wanted to hear her take on why &quot;Millennials&quot; aren't as prominent in the political landscape as they should be. You can’t argue with the numbers: People under 30 make up 17% of the population (that excludes children); yet, they provide less than 2% of all members of parliament, and rarely hold high political office. I wanted to know from Ciara: What are the problems young people encounter when getting politically active and how can more young people get a seat at the table? &amp;nbsp; Ciara, there's a common misconception that young people are simply not interested in politics. Do you think this is true? It’s a really easy statement to accept and not question too much, but I don’t agree. What needs to be understood is that there is a difference between party politics and politics. Yes, it is true that young people are not hugely involved with party politics, though I do think there is significant underreporting taking place. We see young people highly active online about a range of policy issues and structural reform on a daily basis. But, in the broader area of politics that encompasses issues, activism and civic engagement, I do think young people are highly engaged. It is just not easy to quantify the level of engagement in terms of membership numbers and so on, because that is not the way it works. Young people are much more tuned in nowadays that we give ourselves credit for. We saw it here in Ireland in 2015, when the marriage equality referendum was taking place. The backbone of the equality side was a young demographic - they were the most vocal, the most unabashed. That’s being pretty interested in politics I would say. Once you get down to it, politics is nothing more than people operating with each other, connecting and trying to represent. There isn’t much about that that young people can’t relate to. And yet, party memberships are steadily declining. Why? Are political parties dead? Can they be revived? Yes, this is something that I find particularly interesting to talk about and dissect. Young people definitely love an issue-based campaign. Anything that we can see a solution for or something that we cause an impact on, we’ll be onboard with. Like the marriage equality referendum of 2015 I referred to, and more recently the referendum on the 8th amendment, which saw loads of people become politically engaged. This weirdly doesn’t seem to translate to party politics, nor to local and general elections. I think party membership is affected by cynicism. It’s very hard to make a dent in the long established political wheel. Instead, the temptation would be to run as an independent candidate or even form your own party. We saw this case with Renua in the last Irish General Election. But they were wiped out across the board, as the electorate didn’t see a past, present or future for them. This happens in many countries across Europe too, as we constantly see new parties rise and fall virtually overnight. Is it disheartening trying to get into politics? Most definitely. But should people just give up? Absolutely not. Why do you think it is important for young people to take an interest in politics, and more importantly, to take action? It’s pretty straight forward for me. Politics impacts nearly all aspects of our lives. It’s not something a lot of us see, until we start working or maybe get to college. But it is so important to be tuned in to politics and the repercussions of it. Politics forms the frame of our lives, and the earlier people get involved, the better they will be able to impact on that framing. Now, I’m certainly not advocating that everyone should be affiliated with party politics or should hold strong opinions on policy or anything but... I think we need to help people understand that politics and governments' decisions have big impacts on everyone in society. It’s scary to me at times to see how passive we can be about this. Is it a lack of understanding or is it years of feeling wronged by big party politics? Maybe a mixture of both even. Young people today, so-called Millennials, are under-represented in political decision making. Why do you think this is the case, and what can be done to fix it? I hate to use the dreaded Q word but are quotas the answer? Should each party or elected committee have a person who is aged between 18-25 or 20-30? The challenge is that we need more young people running, for more young people to be elected. Most things don’t require complex solutions but only pretty simple ones. I think we should consider offering funding and scholarships for aspiring young politicians. Giving them support so they can succeed, instead of making it easier for them to fail. Is the future of politics happening online? What is the importance of offline people-to-people relationships? Campaign strategist Guillaume Liegey talks about Data/Tech/Human to describe the way in which offline face-to-face contact in the community or on the doorsteps fits into the data infrastructure of political organisations. They are not separate - they are connected and supportive of each other. In the same way, if you were to conduct all of your political interactions exclusively online, you would miss whole sections of society that do not interact there. At present, nothing really beats face-to-face interaction. I love online platforms like Twitter and Instagram, but there is always going to be something lacking. Real life conversations can’t be as easily misconstrued as online ones. How many times a day do we see tone being taken up incorrectly online, no matter how many emojis you use! There will always be a place online for politics and the discussion surrounding it, but ultimately the action we want to see implemented off the back of it will happen offline. It’s always more effort to do things away from a keyboard. but the results are always a little bit better. How do you engage politically? How did you get started? There is so many different ways to be involved in politics. I always admire people who operate on the frontline and the activists who drive the movements that are close to their own hearts. I would see myself as being very civically minded, and I enjoy working on a local basis in my own community at home. No matter the organisation - grassroots is a fundamental in being successful. At Ecanvasser, we see ourselves as being architects of democracy. Working as technicians in the political software sector is a great place to be at the moment, because you get to be fully immersed in the campaign cycle. Working with new candidates as they begin their campaigns means you can learn so much and you can also turn all these learnings into useful resources to push out to the next generation of candidates. What is your motivation for supporting &quot;political beginners&quot; with free resources and advice? Where did you gain that expertise? The company mission at Ecanvasser is about allowing anyone to run for office. The barrier of entry being lowered is something we spoke about 4 years ago and still talk about everyday in the office. People need to understand that politics is collaborative. So why not share all the useful tips you have to help people reach their goals! That’s why our Campaign Blueprint section is one of our most utilised sections on our website and also why we feel the need to constantly share videos on our Youtube channel. Everything changes so quickly between election cycles, it’s important for us to always be evolving and trying to stay on trend. What is your #1 advice for young people who want to get politically involved, but don‘t know where and how to get started? I think we - all of us, and maybe especially young people - don’t realise the value that we have, whether that is in a work context or in civil society. If you think you are going to be an addition somewhere instead of  subtraction, get involved! I think some young people really have that “fear factor” when it comes to putting themselves out there to be judged. We need to lose this and just go for it. It’s as simple as this: you have to start somewhere - so start by joining an issue group or organisation that you are passionate about. Think of politics as an apprenticeship for life, there is so much to learn and many avenues that you can explore. Consider an area that you want to impact and research groups in that area. &amp;nbsp; Thank you Ciara for this insightful conversation!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Politics: The Youth Factor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/politics-the-youth-factor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Politics: The Youth Factor" /><published>2018-07-12T20:00:47+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-12T20:00:47+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/politics-the-youth-factor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/politics-the-youth-factor/">&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to be political these days? How can someone get politically engaged - especially if they don't know where even to get started?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to Ciara O'Riordan about all these things recently. Read here some excerpts, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecanvasser.com/blog/millennials-and-politics/&quot;&gt;check out the full interview here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;4beingpoliticallyactivecanmeansomuchmorethanrunningforlocalofficeandtryingtogetelectedwhatotheravenuescanyoungpeoplewhoareinterestedinpoliticstaketobecomemorepoliticallyimmersed&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ciara O'Riordan:&lt;/strong&gt; Being politically active can mean so much more than running for local office and trying to get elected. What other avenues can young people who are interested in politics take to become more politically immersed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christina Wunder:&lt;/strong&gt; Indeed, there are many other forms of political action. That could be campaigning ahead of a referendum. It could also mean supporting an environmental cause, volunteering in your community or taking part in charity activities. It can be speaking up and calling others out when injustice is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes even talking about something can become powerful political action. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pF72px2R3Hg&quot;&gt;Lauren Singer&lt;/a&gt; for example, started to document her transition towards a zero-waste lifestyle back in 2012. Through her blog and YouTube channel, she reaches millions of people and encourages them to produce less waste. She does so by suggesting simple and easy-to-follow steps – from avoiding disposable coffee cups to creating your own package-free products. She lobbies for more sustainable waste management, and does advocacy work for example with the United Nations or UNICEF. I find it inspiring to see how something that seems small at the beginning, can grow into powerful action. That's why we always have to remember, everything starts with taking a small first step – and the stamina to keep at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, my advice to everyone who wants to get politically active would be to start with small, easy and doable steps. Try to read and learn more about the issue you care about. What’s the story behind it? What are the problems, and what could be potential solutions? Are there people or organizations that are already trying to do something about it? Who are they? Who are the people and institutions in charge? Could you reach out to them? In this book “Lobbying for change”, the activist &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alemannoEU&quot;&gt;Alberto Alemanno&lt;/a&gt; suggests a step-by-step guide on how to get active and have an impact on something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecanvasser.com/blog/millennials-and-politics/&quot;&gt;Read the full conversation here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">What does it mean to be political these days? How can someone get politically engaged - especially if they don't know where even to get started? I spoke to Ciara O'Riordan about all these things recently. Read here some excerpts, or check out the full interview here. &amp;nbsp; Ciara O'Riordan: Being politically active can mean so much more than running for local office and trying to get elected. What other avenues can young people who are interested in politics take to become more politically immersed? Christina Wunder: Indeed, there are many other forms of political action. That could be campaigning ahead of a referendum. It could also mean supporting an environmental cause, volunteering in your community or taking part in charity activities. It can be speaking up and calling others out when injustice is done. Sometimes even talking about something can become powerful political action. Lauren Singer for example, started to document her transition towards a zero-waste lifestyle back in 2012. Through her blog and YouTube channel, she reaches millions of people and encourages them to produce less waste. She does so by suggesting simple and easy-to-follow steps – from avoiding disposable coffee cups to creating your own package-free products. She lobbies for more sustainable waste management, and does advocacy work for example with the United Nations or UNICEF. I find it inspiring to see how something that seems small at the beginning, can grow into powerful action. That's why we always have to remember, everything starts with taking a small first step – and the stamina to keep at it. Therefore, my advice to everyone who wants to get politically active would be to start with small, easy and doable steps. Try to read and learn more about the issue you care about. What’s the story behind it? What are the problems, and what could be potential solutions? Are there people or organizations that are already trying to do something about it? Who are they? Who are the people and institutions in charge? Could you reach out to them? In this book “Lobbying for change”, the activist Alberto Alemanno suggests a step-by-step guide on how to get active and have an impact on something. &amp;nbsp; Read the full conversation here. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Millennials and politics go together?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/millennials-and-politics-terry-reintke/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Millennials and politics go together?" /><published>2018-05-28T07:45:03+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-28T07:45:03+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/millennials-and-politics-terry-reintke</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/millennials-and-politics-terry-reintke/">&lt;p&gt;Young people don't care about politics, right? Ah these Millennials, they just want their daily dose of Instagram - and otherwise be left in peace from all your talk of political parties, populism or pensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, actually, that is simply not true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Young people are more interested in politics than you think&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young people (12-25) are indeed increasingly interested in politics and the world around them (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://s08.static-shell.com/content/dam/royaldutchshell/documents/corporate/flyer-zur-shell-jugendstudie-2015-auf-englisch.pdf&quot;&gt;17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Shell Youth Study, p.4&lt;/a&gt;). With one caveat: they are just not as fond of the classic, old-school system of party politics. Or else, if they do want to get involved, they often don't know where and how to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While political apathy is on the rise in general, I can see why a person in their twenties may struggle to identify with their elected representatives, who are, on average, well into their fifties - both &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eu40.eu/young-meps-call-for-more-power-and-mandates/&quot;&gt;in Europe&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/democratic-governance/parliamentary_development/the-global-parliamentary-report.html&quot;&gt;in the world&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Among the over 750 EU parliamentarians, young people are clearly under-represented - with less than 2% being under 30&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of 751 EU parliamentarians, 83 (or 11%) are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eu40.eu/young-meps-call-for-more-power-and-mandates/&quot;&gt;younger than 40 years old&lt;/a&gt;. Of these, only 12 are under 30. That's less than 2%, and figures for the rest of the world are very similar. Meanwhile, the equivalent share of young people (excluding children) in Europe is &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php?title=Being_young_in_Europe_today_-_demographic_trends&quot;&gt;17.4 %&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is of course not a problem in itself, because there are many other factors at play when determining whether you trust someone to represent you: experience, relevant party affiliation, regional or cultural background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But nevertheless, it is striking that we are this badly underrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are not a whole lot of young people in and around decision-making, it is important that we at least know who those few are – what they do, what they stand for and what they believe in. So I started meeting them for coffee and asking them about their work. The first one that I would like to introduce is Terry. She shared a few insights into her work, her career and day-to-day life as a parliamentarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Terry Reintke, 31, parliamentarian for the European green party&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terry became an elected member of the European parliament in 2014. One of the things she has been fighting for since then is the rights of young people. For example, she launched an EU campaign to improve the often poor working conditions of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MSmuBN3j0fs&quot;&gt;interns&lt;/a&gt; (well, don't we all know that the struggle is real).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we would all agree: internships are a very useful thing, especially during or just after university. You can learn a lot, gain some hands-on experience, and ideally use it as a stepping stone into your first &quot;real job&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you’re stuck in a loop of internships until your late twenties or even early thirties? What if finding a junior- or entry-level job is depends upon completing several internships? What if these (de-facto mandatory) internships are underpaid or even completely unpaid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then this can pose real existential problems - especially for those whose parents simply cannot afford to pay their children's rent and food in expensive cities, while they are working long days without remuneration. What’s more: often they must do this without certainty about their future prospects for a paid job. It limits the access of less privileged people to quality jobs and perpetuates societal inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Generation Internship – the struggle is real&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This video is in German - activate the English subtitles in the bottom bar.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MSmuBN3j0fs&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terry knows what a struggle it can be to start out in the job market after your studies, both from her friends, as well as from her own experience. Before running for the 2014 European elections, she was unemployed, which was not an easy time for her. &quot;This was a challenge obviously, because I had very little money and resources.&quot; At some point, working for free is simply not an option any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as an EU parliament member, Terry is working to make a difference - and not only for the young. Her own roots are in the German &quot;Ruhrgebiet&quot;, one of Germany's weaker and disadvantaged regions. In her role as an EU parliamentarian, she advocates for strengthening and developing Europe’s regions - to ensure that they don't fall increasingly behind when it comes to competing for people, companies and investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;#metoo - EU edition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terry Reintke is a staunch supporter of women's rights. In 2017, she initiated the campaign #metooEU and started a debate on sexualised violence in the European Parliament by sharing her own very personal story of having been sexually harassed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Time Magazine nominated her &lt;a href=&quot;http://time.com/time-person-of-the-year-2017-silence-breakers/&quot;&gt;“Person of the Year”&lt;/a&gt;, alongside other activists, politicians and celebrities such as Taylor Swift, Alyssa Milano and Amal Clooney. Terry describes this as one of the most inspiring and rewarding moments of her political life: &quot;Reading the issue of the TIME magazine and seeing my picture among all those inspiring 'Silence Breakers' who spoke up against sexual harassment was for sure a special moment in my life.&quot; However, being heard is not enough. She says: &quot;What is more important is seeing reforms being implemented. Seeing actual change happen after our #metoo-campaign - that is what was important for me.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These moments of success make it all worthwhile, even when the road can at times be long and exhausting. &quot;Our everyday work is of course much less glamorous than being in a glossy magazine&quot;. This is also the case when she works on laws to improve the rights of workers, and to protect them better from being exploited in the labour market. &quot;Sitting in long meetings negotiating positive rules for the European labour market might not look as exciting, but it can still be absolutely rewarding.&quot; Terry's ultimate goal: &quot;To change the reality of European citizens to the better. That’s what really matters.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that though, a politician needs to understand what really matters to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Listening to people is key&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in touch with citizens and politicians has never been as easy as today. Social media such as Twitter, Facebook or YouTube are offering the tools for politicians to not only present their work in an accessible way or reply to citizen's questions. Now they can ask questions themselves and request direct input from citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before an important debate in the EU parliament, Terry sometimes asks her &quot;followers&quot; for issues or questions they want her to raise in that debate. The feedback she receives helps her to do her work better. &quot;I like to stay in touch with people as much as possible. Through social media, speeches, debates, but also meetings in everyday life. I travel a lot in my work, and I try to get in touch with as many people as possible. In fact, most of my positions, speeches and demands come from discussions with citizens. At the end of the day, I am not in the parliament for myself, but for them.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for the regular work of an EU parliamentarian. However, coming back to the under-representation of young people in political decision-making, I wonder: how can Millennials get more involved? What is Terry's advice for young people who want to engage, but don't know how to get started?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How can Millennials get more politically involved?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on her own experience, Terry explains: &quot;What helped me was a network of strong people, mostly women, who supported me in my candidacy. They did so politically, as well as emotionally. Because in a campaign - or in fact when working on any project or trying something new - you will always make mistakes. Things that you did not expect will suddenly pop up. It is impossible to be prepared for everything, but still, we very often believe that we have to be. That keeps a lot of people - especially women or young people - from trying it in the first place. My number one piece of advice: Trust in your ability to improvise and to get through crap times. To find energy to get up again, even after you have failed in something. When you are ready for that, you have nothing to worry about.&lt;br /&gt;
To a person that wants to make a difference and shape politics, I would say: find out what you are really passionate about. You will have to spend a lot of time talking, reading, discussing and arguing about it. So you really have to like it. Then make a plan. I love making plans, and in fact, that really helped me to strategise. Think about what you want to change and how you will make it happen.&lt;br /&gt;
And well, be prepared to fail at first. And fail again. Eventually, it is going to work out. Not achieving something teaches you more that getting somewhere ever will.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What about you?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Terry was elected in 2014, the numbers of young parliamentarians in the world have improved slightly. Worldwide, members of parliament aged under 30 went up from 1.6% in 2014 to 1.9% 2016. In the same period, the share of those that are under 40 years old went up from 12.9% to 14.2%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is hope, but there is still a long way to go. Young people are not only underrepresented in politics, but they also abstain from elections much more than older people - thereby giving up their shot at shaping the world before even trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But look at the recent developments in the world: From Brexit to the United States' decision to pull out of the Paris climate agreement – politicians are making decisions that will affect us young people's futures for years and generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Parliament_election,_2019&quot;&gt;23-26 May 2019&lt;/a&gt;, there will be European elections in the EU; let's make sure our voices, views and interests are taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">Young people don't care about politics, right? Ah these Millennials, they just want their daily dose of Instagram - and otherwise be left in peace from all your talk of political parties, populism or pensions. Well, actually, that is simply not true. Young people are more interested in politics than you think Young people (12-25) are indeed increasingly interested in politics and the world around them (see 17th Shell Youth Study, p.4). With one caveat: they are just not as fond of the classic, old-school system of party politics. Or else, if they do want to get involved, they often don't know where and how to begin. While political apathy is on the rise in general, I can see why a person in their twenties may struggle to identify with their elected representatives, who are, on average, well into their fifties - both in Europe, as well as in the world. Among the over 750 EU parliamentarians, young people are clearly under-represented - with less than 2% being under 30 Out of 751 EU parliamentarians, 83 (or 11%) are younger than 40 years old. Of these, only 12 are under 30. That's less than 2%, and figures for the rest of the world are very similar. Meanwhile, the equivalent share of young people (excluding children) in Europe is 17.4 %. This is of course not a problem in itself, because there are many other factors at play when determining whether you trust someone to represent you: experience, relevant party affiliation, regional or cultural background. But nevertheless, it is striking that we are this badly underrepresented. If there are not a whole lot of young people in and around decision-making, it is important that we at least know who those few are – what they do, what they stand for and what they believe in. So I started meeting them for coffee and asking them about their work. The first one that I would like to introduce is Terry. She shared a few insights into her work, her career and day-to-day life as a parliamentarian. Terry Reintke, 31, parliamentarian for the European green party Terry became an elected member of the European parliament in 2014. One of the things she has been fighting for since then is the rights of young people. For example, she launched an EU campaign to improve the often poor working conditions of interns (well, don't we all know that the struggle is real). I think we would all agree: internships are a very useful thing, especially during or just after university. You can learn a lot, gain some hands-on experience, and ideally use it as a stepping stone into your first &quot;real job&quot;. But what if you’re stuck in a loop of internships until your late twenties or even early thirties? What if finding a junior- or entry-level job is depends upon completing several internships? What if these (de-facto mandatory) internships are underpaid or even completely unpaid? Then this can pose real existential problems - especially for those whose parents simply cannot afford to pay their children's rent and food in expensive cities, while they are working long days without remuneration. What’s more: often they must do this without certainty about their future prospects for a paid job. It limits the access of less privileged people to quality jobs and perpetuates societal inequalities. Generation Internship – the struggle is real (This video is in German - activate the English subtitles in the bottom bar.) Terry knows what a struggle it can be to start out in the job market after your studies, both from her friends, as well as from her own experience. Before running for the 2014 European elections, she was unemployed, which was not an easy time for her. &quot;This was a challenge obviously, because I had very little money and resources.&quot; At some point, working for free is simply not an option any more. Now, as an EU parliament member, Terry is working to make a difference - and not only for the young. Her own roots are in the German &quot;Ruhrgebiet&quot;, one of Germany's weaker and disadvantaged regions. In her role as an EU parliamentarian, she advocates for strengthening and developing Europe’s regions - to ensure that they don't fall increasingly behind when it comes to competing for people, companies and investment. #metoo - EU edition Terry Reintke is a staunch supporter of women's rights. In 2017, she initiated the campaign #metooEU and started a debate on sexualised violence in the European Parliament by sharing her own very personal story of having been sexually harassed. The American Time Magazine nominated her “Person of the Year”, alongside other activists, politicians and celebrities such as Taylor Swift, Alyssa Milano and Amal Clooney. Terry describes this as one of the most inspiring and rewarding moments of her political life: &quot;Reading the issue of the TIME magazine and seeing my picture among all those inspiring 'Silence Breakers' who spoke up against sexual harassment was for sure a special moment in my life.&quot; However, being heard is not enough. She says: &quot;What is more important is seeing reforms being implemented. Seeing actual change happen after our #metoo-campaign - that is what was important for me.&quot; These moments of success make it all worthwhile, even when the road can at times be long and exhausting. &quot;Our everyday work is of course much less glamorous than being in a glossy magazine&quot;. This is also the case when she works on laws to improve the rights of workers, and to protect them better from being exploited in the labour market. &quot;Sitting in long meetings negotiating positive rules for the European labour market might not look as exciting, but it can still be absolutely rewarding.&quot; Terry's ultimate goal: &quot;To change the reality of European citizens to the better. That’s what really matters.&quot; To do that though, a politician needs to understand what really matters to them. Listening to people is key Being in touch with citizens and politicians has never been as easy as today. Social media such as Twitter, Facebook or YouTube are offering the tools for politicians to not only present their work in an accessible way or reply to citizen's questions. Now they can ask questions themselves and request direct input from citizens. Before an important debate in the EU parliament, Terry sometimes asks her &quot;followers&quot; for issues or questions they want her to raise in that debate. The feedback she receives helps her to do her work better. &quot;I like to stay in touch with people as much as possible. Through social media, speeches, debates, but also meetings in everyday life. I travel a lot in my work, and I try to get in touch with as many people as possible. In fact, most of my positions, speeches and demands come from discussions with citizens. At the end of the day, I am not in the parliament for myself, but for them.&quot; So much for the regular work of an EU parliamentarian. However, coming back to the under-representation of young people in political decision-making, I wonder: how can Millennials get more involved? What is Terry's advice for young people who want to engage, but don't know how to get started? How can Millennials get more politically involved? Based on her own experience, Terry explains: &quot;What helped me was a network of strong people, mostly women, who supported me in my candidacy. They did so politically, as well as emotionally. Because in a campaign - or in fact when working on any project or trying something new - you will always make mistakes. Things that you did not expect will suddenly pop up. It is impossible to be prepared for everything, but still, we very often believe that we have to be. That keeps a lot of people - especially women or young people - from trying it in the first place. My number one piece of advice: Trust in your ability to improvise and to get through crap times. To find energy to get up again, even after you have failed in something. When you are ready for that, you have nothing to worry about. To a person that wants to make a difference and shape politics, I would say: find out what you are really passionate about. You will have to spend a lot of time talking, reading, discussing and arguing about it. So you really have to like it. Then make a plan. I love making plans, and in fact, that really helped me to strategise. Think about what you want to change and how you will make it happen. And well, be prepared to fail at first. And fail again. Eventually, it is going to work out. Not achieving something teaches you more that getting somewhere ever will.&quot; What about you? Since Terry was elected in 2014, the numbers of young parliamentarians in the world have improved slightly. Worldwide, members of parliament aged under 30 went up from 1.6% in 2014 to 1.9% 2016. In the same period, the share of those that are under 40 years old went up from 12.9% to 14.2%. There is hope, but there is still a long way to go. Young people are not only underrepresented in politics, but they also abstain from elections much more than older people - thereby giving up their shot at shaping the world before even trying. But look at the recent developments in the world: From Brexit to the United States' decision to pull out of the Paris climate agreement – politicians are making decisions that will affect us young people's futures for years and generations to come. On 23-26 May 2019, there will be European elections in the EU; let's make sure our voices, views and interests are taken into account. &amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Tips to make your internship a success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/4-tips-to-make-your-internship-a-success/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Tips to make your internship a success" /><published>2018-03-13T16:09:53+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-13T16:09:53+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/4-tips-to-make-your-internship-a-success</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/4-tips-to-make-your-internship-a-success/">&lt;p&gt;During my university studies I did two traineeships. One was underpaid, the other one was unpaid all together. But hey, &lt;del&gt;beggars, eh,&lt;/del&gt; young professionals can't be choosers, and thanks to the German system of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.studentenwerke.de/en/content/baf%C3%B6g-state-funding-students-germany&quot;&gt;affordable student loans&lt;/a&gt;, I didn't have to fear for my financial existence too much. So I had the chance to try out a couple of things and just take my first rookie steps in the professional world. Let's face it: university does not really prepare you for the real job world out there. After graduating from my Masters degree, I managed to nail what was then my best traineeship so far: a paid one. It was with the European Commission, which offers traineeships every 6 months pays and pays their interns a fair and decent allowance of around €1100. This was enough for me to get a flat-share room in Brussels - while not having to sell off my left kidney to pay the rent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Internship is what you make of it.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that a successful internship is determined by four factors. You don't have a whole lot of influence over &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them, but I'd say that at least half of it depends on what you make of it - and 50% of creative leeway is a lot. Make sure to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Your internship is what you make of it! Here's 4 tips to make it a success:&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let's say you managed to get a good internship and are motivated to make it a success. What's next? How do you ensure that it will actually help you to advance on your career - rather than just becoming a gap-filler on your CV? Here's the factors that I think matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. A decent pay (or something like that)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's be clear: None of us do internships to get rich - but rather to learn from them. Nevertheless, your financial situation shouldn't cause you sleepless nights, and being able to pay your rent and not starve is a plus. I admit that - apart from the fact that it is you who decides what internship offers to accept or decline - you don't have too much influence over this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not in all sectors do young people have the luxury to be very picky. But if you have any kind of scope to negotiate, do it. Maybe you can get them to pay a small allowance towards &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/en/10-tips-when-you-move-to-a-new-city-for-a-job/&quot;&gt;your accommodation&lt;/a&gt;, free lunches in their canteen or any other useful benefits? See what can be done, asking won't cost you anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if all of the above is not possible, it's all the more reason to make an extra effort to make the internship worth your time: by learning as much as you can during that time. Which leads me to point 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. The learnings you are offered and how you're integrated in the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Spoiler: Being able to finally make the perfect coffee after six months is not what constitutes for a successful traineeship.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we agree: having a degree alone is not a guarantee for succeeding in the workplace. It is very unlikely for a university programme to deliver all the skills and competences that you will need along your career path. This is why internships are so valuable, especially when you don't have much experience on the job yet. You can try out different sectors and disciplines and see, if that's even a good match for you. What I found particularly useful when starting out as an intern was to observe how people work and deal with professional challenges, to compare different styles of working and to find my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in order to do that, your superiors and colleagues have to make an effort to integrate you into the team. I know myself that, faced with the challenges of a busy working schedule, keeping the intern in the loop is not your top priority when you're stressed. Often it is also easier to &quot;very quickly do something yourself&quot;, instead of first explaining it to someone for half an hour. But it goes without saying that this is not at all useful for you, the intern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if despite all good intentions, your team doesn't involve you enough in their day-to-day business, talk to them. Remind them of your presence and eagerness to work in a proactive, friendly but not obtrusive way. If they can't think of interesting tasks for you to do immediately, ask them for background information or documents that can help you to better understand the project at hand. Be creative, think of concrete proposals on how to get involved and support them in their work. For example: &quot;In the last team meeting you mentioned that you needed an in-depth analysis of XYZ; I did some research and this is what I put together...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask for feedback. Especially at the beginning, it is likely that you won't deliver right away exactly what is needed, and how it is needed. That's absolutely normal. Every team has different dynamics and practices, and every colleague has a different style of working. Over time, you will understand better how to get involved and figure out ways to add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Finding opportunities to add value - ideally even after your internship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most valuable tip that I got from my supervisor as an intern was: try to find a project for you to pursue during your six months here. Something that you can work towards, and which will be useful for the team even after you're gone. A project that you will be able to take home as your very own success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks into your internship you will hopefully already have been entrusted with a few tasks, as well as better understand who needs what, when and how. Work hard, and fulfil your tasks as good as you can. Whenever you find yourself having nothing to do, look proactively for things you could do to support your team's work or to help improve the quality of their work. Trust me: every office has a long list of &quot;we should&quot;- or &quot;would be good&quot;-tasks that nobody ever finds the time for. But if done well, these little jobs can improve the quality of the whole team's work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe your team is lacking a comprehensive social-media-strategy? Maybe they would need a better monitoring-method to keep track of what is working and what is not? Maybe you could put together an analysis, including concrete and easy-to-follow steps on how to do it best? This was the project I did during my first internship. In my subsequent job interviews, I didn't dread the question &quot;tell us about some of your professional successes&quot; as much as I used to before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are young and full of skills and knowledge that your colleagues might not have. Digital and social media skills are the first things that come to mind, but I'm sure there's much more if you give it some thought. You have the luxurious position that, firstly, you are not yet swallowed up and blinded by old routines, and secondly, that you actually have the time to do some research and get creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk to your superiors and/or colleagues about your project ideas and try to find something that will add value to the team's daily work and that will ideally even still be used after your traineeship is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. What you take home from it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the time after your internship, which is when ideally you should be starting to search for real jobs. Everybody knows that there are two extremes among interns: those who laze around all day and wait for the 6 months to pass, and those who are proactive and become close to full staff members, who actively participate in the team's tasks and take on responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build your case to show that you're one of the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it: what are the most common horrible questions in a job interview? &quot;What were your biggest professional successes so far?&quot; &quot;Tell us about the projects you have successfully worked on&quot;, &quot;What challenges have you mastered in your professional life, and how did you do that?&quot; ...and so on. Just because you don't have 15 years of experience on the job, it does not mean that you cannot reply to these questions with concrete and convincing examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of your internship, keep stock and make a list of tasks and projects that you have successfully mastered, and where you have managed to assume some responsibility. You don't want to find yourself applying for your next job, staring at an empty word-document and failing to remember examples that would help you to prove that you possess all the competencies and experiences that are asked for in the job description. Jotting those things down in a notebook during your internship can help you keeping track of these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most important tip of all: Trust in yourself and your skills. You'll see, you will manage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anything else?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I forget anything? Do you have further tips and recommendations? What is your experience with internships? Let me know in the comments section below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and don't forget to spread the word:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;4 Tips to make your internship a success&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">During my university studies I did two traineeships. One was underpaid, the other one was unpaid all together. But hey, beggars, eh, young professionals can't be choosers, and thanks to the German system of affordable student loans, I didn't have to fear for my financial existence too much. So I had the chance to try out a couple of things and just take my first rookie steps in the professional world. Let's face it: university does not really prepare you for the real job world out there. After graduating from my Masters degree, I managed to nail what was then my best traineeship so far: a paid one. It was with the European Commission, which offers traineeships every 6 months pays and pays their interns a fair and decent allowance of around €1100. This was enough for me to get a flat-share room in Brussels - while not having to sell off my left kidney to pay the rent. Internship is what you make of it. I believe that a successful internship is determined by four factors. You don't have a whole lot of influence over all of them, but I'd say that at least half of it depends on what you make of it - and 50% of creative leeway is a lot. Make sure to use it. [bctt tweet=&quot;Your internship is what you make of it! Here's 4 tips to make it a success:&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;] So let's say you managed to get a good internship and are motivated to make it a success. What's next? How do you ensure that it will actually help you to advance on your career - rather than just becoming a gap-filler on your CV? Here's the factors that I think matter: 1. A decent pay (or something like that) Let's be clear: None of us do internships to get rich - but rather to learn from them. Nevertheless, your financial situation shouldn't cause you sleepless nights, and being able to pay your rent and not starve is a plus. I admit that - apart from the fact that it is you who decides what internship offers to accept or decline - you don't have too much influence over this. Not in all sectors do young people have the luxury to be very picky. But if you have any kind of scope to negotiate, do it. Maybe you can get them to pay a small allowance towards your accommodation, free lunches in their canteen or any other useful benefits? See what can be done, asking won't cost you anything. And if all of the above is not possible, it's all the more reason to make an extra effort to make the internship worth your time: by learning as much as you can during that time. Which leads me to point 2: 2. The learnings you are offered and how you're integrated in the team (Spoiler: Being able to finally make the perfect coffee after six months is not what constitutes for a successful traineeship.) I think we agree: having a degree alone is not a guarantee for succeeding in the workplace. It is very unlikely for a university programme to deliver all the skills and competences that you will need along your career path. This is why internships are so valuable, especially when you don't have much experience on the job yet. You can try out different sectors and disciplines and see, if that's even a good match for you. What I found particularly useful when starting out as an intern was to observe how people work and deal with professional challenges, to compare different styles of working and to find my own. But in order to do that, your superiors and colleagues have to make an effort to integrate you into the team. I know myself that, faced with the challenges of a busy working schedule, keeping the intern in the loop is not your top priority when you're stressed. Often it is also easier to &quot;very quickly do something yourself&quot;, instead of first explaining it to someone for half an hour. But it goes without saying that this is not at all useful for you, the intern. So if despite all good intentions, your team doesn't involve you enough in their day-to-day business, talk to them. Remind them of your presence and eagerness to work in a proactive, friendly but not obtrusive way. If they can't think of interesting tasks for you to do immediately, ask them for background information or documents that can help you to better understand the project at hand. Be creative, think of concrete proposals on how to get involved and support them in their work. For example: &quot;In the last team meeting you mentioned that you needed an in-depth analysis of XYZ; I did some research and this is what I put together...&quot; Ask for feedback. Especially at the beginning, it is likely that you won't deliver right away exactly what is needed, and how it is needed. That's absolutely normal. Every team has different dynamics and practices, and every colleague has a different style of working. Over time, you will understand better how to get involved and figure out ways to add value. 3. Finding opportunities to add value - ideally even after your internship The most valuable tip that I got from my supervisor as an intern was: try to find a project for you to pursue during your six months here. Something that you can work towards, and which will be useful for the team even after you're gone. A project that you will be able to take home as your very own success. A couple of weeks into your internship you will hopefully already have been entrusted with a few tasks, as well as better understand who needs what, when and how. Work hard, and fulfil your tasks as good as you can. Whenever you find yourself having nothing to do, look proactively for things you could do to support your team's work or to help improve the quality of their work. Trust me: every office has a long list of &quot;we should&quot;- or &quot;would be good&quot;-tasks that nobody ever finds the time for. But if done well, these little jobs can improve the quality of the whole team's work. Maybe your team is lacking a comprehensive social-media-strategy? Maybe they would need a better monitoring-method to keep track of what is working and what is not? Maybe you could put together an analysis, including concrete and easy-to-follow steps on how to do it best? This was the project I did during my first internship. In my subsequent job interviews, I didn't dread the question &quot;tell us about some of your professional successes&quot; as much as I used to before. You are young and full of skills and knowledge that your colleagues might not have. Digital and social media skills are the first things that come to mind, but I'm sure there's much more if you give it some thought. You have the luxurious position that, firstly, you are not yet swallowed up and blinded by old routines, and secondly, that you actually have the time to do some research and get creative. Talk to your superiors and/or colleagues about your project ideas and try to find something that will add value to the team's daily work and that will ideally even still be used after your traineeship is over. 4. What you take home from it Think about the time after your internship, which is when ideally you should be starting to search for real jobs. Everybody knows that there are two extremes among interns: those who laze around all day and wait for the 6 months to pass, and those who are proactive and become close to full staff members, who actively participate in the team's tasks and take on responsibility. Build your case to show that you're one of the latter. Think about it: what are the most common horrible questions in a job interview? &quot;What were your biggest professional successes so far?&quot; &quot;Tell us about the projects you have successfully worked on&quot;, &quot;What challenges have you mastered in your professional life, and how did you do that?&quot; ...and so on. Just because you don't have 15 years of experience on the job, it does not mean that you cannot reply to these questions with concrete and convincing examples. Over the course of your internship, keep stock and make a list of tasks and projects that you have successfully mastered, and where you have managed to assume some responsibility. You don't want to find yourself applying for your next job, staring at an empty word-document and failing to remember examples that would help you to prove that you possess all the competencies and experiences that are asked for in the job description. Jotting those things down in a notebook during your internship can help you keeping track of these things. But most important tip of all: Trust in yourself and your skills. You'll see, you will manage. Anything else? Did I forget anything? Do you have further tips and recommendations? What is your experience with internships? Let me know in the comments section below. Oh, and don't forget to spread the word: [bctt tweet=&quot;4 Tips to make your internship a success&quot; username=&quot;christinawunder&quot;]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dear working mums, there’s something I want to tell you</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dear-working-mums/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dear working mums, there's something I want to tell you" /><published>2018-03-08T07:27:19+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-08T07:27:19+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dear-working-mums</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dear-working-mums/">&lt;p&gt;Dear working mum colleague,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had the honour of meeting you in almost every of my jobs so far. You are an intelligent woman, good at what you do, and you have a kid (or more than one). You're either nice or you suck, you have a sense of humour or you don't. You have your moments of success and crisis in your career, have productive and unproductive days. You have your ups and downs, like all of us. In short: you are just like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet there is one thing that divides you from all of us (and by &quot;us&quot; I mean colleagues without children as well as most male colleagues with children): you feel guilty. All the time and for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your constant companion: your guilt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You feel guilty because it's not you who is helping your son with his everyday maths homework, but the private tutor. You feel guilty, because the muffins, which you pack for your daughter's nursery party, are from Marks&amp;amp;Spencer, and not home-made. You feel guilty whenever you have to leave the office early. And equally guilty, when you don't manage to do so, and your daughter now has to wait for you for 15 minutes with the grumpy kindergarden teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are constantly carrying this heavy load called 'guilt', which no young professional in her mid-twenties and no successful career-Dad really knows. Because the term 'bad mother' is reserved for women, who work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the daughter of a working mum (as if this was the only thing that defines her identity...) I want to tell you something: you don't have to feel guilty. There is absolutely no reason for that, to be completely honest. Chances are, your kid had a great time in those 15 minutes with the kindergarden teacher, because she enjoyed their full and undivided attention. Your little one will survive this - and I know what I'm talking about, because my mum was just like you. And yes, sometimes I was indeed the last child to be picked up from kindergarden. I remember it well, because I could now have that toy, over which all the kids had been bickering during day, all to myself. It was quite awesome, actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Long live the latchkey child&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, I had our house key on a pretty cool lanyard around my neck (latchkey children rule!) Despite the fact that I would constantly forget, lose or displace it everywhere, I liked it by and large. After school, I would enjoy the silence back home, do my homework - or eat melted cheese sandwiches and watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_HmEGRVUcR0&quot;&gt;Rocko's modern life&lt;/a&gt;. Well, if anyone thinks that this is a horrible and pitiful scenario, I'm sorry, but they must have this life-thing all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear working mum, please don't worry too much. Your offspring will not end up wandering this earth as a lonely and angry individual, just because you're stuck in the office from time to time and don't manage to prepare some whole-food homemade avocado dip for dinner. It's much more likely that your little son is enjoying himself a lot with his auntie, grandpa or the nice neighbours whose son is the same age as yours. The only one who is suffering is you, because you are feeling guilty. Because you are made to believe that you should feel guilty. But isn't it merely healthy when a child has more than one or two caregivers in his or her life? Doesn't it take a village to raise a child?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning to be independent is part of the deal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it just me or have we all forgotten what it was like to be a child? That as a kid you love your parents more than anything and love spending time with them - but that you also embrace those moments of increasing independence? Because they mean adventure and growth? Have we all forgotten those amazing moments, when the initial fear and insecurity made way for feeling bold and strong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many years after my childhood had passed, I was rather surprised, when my mother told me that she had often felt guilty. For working, for being late sometimes, for not being the typical perfect mum (seriously, what is that, anyway?). She told me that she had often asked herself whether we (my sisters and me) reproached her for it. I was honestly surprised, because I had never blamed her for that. No, not even secretly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mum and Dad work. Equally.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite the contrary. Today, I am grateful to her for raising me as the strong and autonomous woman that I am. I am grateful that she has always made me feel like being able and worthy to do anything I want, if I work hard for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that - I am grateful to her for &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt; these values. Being the oldest of three sisters, it was a completely unheard-of concept for me that, for whichever dubious reasons, I should be less worthy or les  capable of achieving the same as a boy (duh!?). Mum and Dad work equally - this is my sense of 'normal'. Because neither of them will receive their paycheck for free, nor will they get their groceries from the supermarket for free. By the way, my Mum earns more than my Dad. It was only much later that I had to learn that for some people, this is offensive (?!#*!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, I am also grateful to my Mum for teaching me how to prepare a halfway healthy dinner in only 10 minutes, if time is short yet again. And that everybody is happier and more satisfied when, instead, you spend some quality time with the family and joke around. Yep, they don't teach you that at school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 'perfect mother' is a myth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear working mum, trust me, it's all going to be fine. Your child will have plenty of opportunities to temporarily hate you - puberty, I'm looking at you - and having picked them up too late from kindergarden will really be the least of your worries. There's no way for you to avert that, even if you were always the first to pick them up, with a toothpaste-commercial-smile on your lips. No, not even if you always bring homemade chocolate cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is one more thing, dear working mum colleague. One thing that I already new before, but which you are proving to the world every day, namely that having a family does not make you less productive, or less dedicated, nor lazy. On the contrary: time pressure is the best way to increase efficiency and learn how to better prioritise. You don't waste time in pointless meetings or with any unimportant nitty-gritty bullshit. You tackle the real stuff; you do it now, and with highest efficiency - because when the working day is over, you have more important things to do than sitting in a dark office and working endless unpaid overtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I advocate for pride, not guilt!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear working mum, please stop blaming yourself. Don't make yourself believe that you are never 'good enough', be it at work or at home. Because you are. Instead, be proud that you lead by example. That you show your children and all of us that life is not over, just because you have kids. That you show your employer, against all prejudices, that people with children don't cease to be full-fledged and valuable team members (this is such an obvious point that I feel silly to even have to say that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Mum is just like you. She also had these feelings of guilt - while I was happily and contentedly eating my melted cheese sandwiches and doing what was my job: growing up, finding my place in this world, and watch cartoons every now and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;All's well that ends well&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have never even thought about being mad at my mother for all this. No, in all modesty, I think she did a pretty good job, I turned out quite ok, didn't I. Had she committed herself to me and only me 24/7 - that wouldn't have helped to eliminate my many flaws and shortcomings. In fact, I think I would have &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I just know one thing: I would be happy, if one day I did just half as good a job as she does - or you or all the other women out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Happy International Women's Day, dear mothers!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><category term="parenthood" /><category term="Stress" /><category term="Work-Life-Balance" /><category term="working mum" /><summary type="html">Dear working mum colleague, I have had the honour of meeting you in almost every of my jobs so far. You are an intelligent woman, good at what you do, and you have a kid (or more than one). You're either nice or you suck, you have a sense of humour or you don't. You have your moments of success and crisis in your career, have productive and unproductive days. You have your ups and downs, like all of us. In short: you are just like everyone else. And yet there is one thing that divides you from all of us (and by &quot;us&quot; I mean colleagues without children as well as most male colleagues with children): you feel guilty. All the time and for everything. Your constant companion: your guilt You feel guilty because it's not you who is helping your son with his everyday maths homework, but the private tutor. You feel guilty, because the muffins, which you pack for your daughter's nursery party, are from Marks&amp;amp;Spencer, and not home-made. You feel guilty whenever you have to leave the office early. And equally guilty, when you don't manage to do so, and your daughter now has to wait for you for 15 minutes with the grumpy kindergarden teacher. You are constantly carrying this heavy load called 'guilt', which no young professional in her mid-twenties and no successful career-Dad really knows. Because the term 'bad mother' is reserved for women, who work. Being the daughter of a working mum (as if this was the only thing that defines her identity...) I want to tell you something: you don't have to feel guilty. There is absolutely no reason for that, to be completely honest. Chances are, your kid had a great time in those 15 minutes with the kindergarden teacher, because she enjoyed their full and undivided attention. Your little one will survive this - and I know what I'm talking about, because my mum was just like you. And yes, sometimes I was indeed the last child to be picked up from kindergarden. I remember it well, because I could now have that toy, over which all the kids had been bickering during day, all to myself. It was quite awesome, actually. Long live the latchkey child Later on, I had our house key on a pretty cool lanyard around my neck (latchkey children rule!) Despite the fact that I would constantly forget, lose or displace it everywhere, I liked it by and large. After school, I would enjoy the silence back home, do my homework - or eat melted cheese sandwiches and watch Rocko's modern life. Well, if anyone thinks that this is a horrible and pitiful scenario, I'm sorry, but they must have this life-thing all wrong. Dear working mum, please don't worry too much. Your offspring will not end up wandering this earth as a lonely and angry individual, just because you're stuck in the office from time to time and don't manage to prepare some whole-food homemade avocado dip for dinner. It's much more likely that your little son is enjoying himself a lot with his auntie, grandpa or the nice neighbours whose son is the same age as yours. The only one who is suffering is you, because you are feeling guilty. Because you are made to believe that you should feel guilty. But isn't it merely healthy when a child has more than one or two caregivers in his or her life? Doesn't it take a village to raise a child? Learning to be independent is part of the deal Is it just me or have we all forgotten what it was like to be a child? That as a kid you love your parents more than anything and love spending time with them - but that you also embrace those moments of increasing independence? Because they mean adventure and growth? Have we all forgotten those amazing moments, when the initial fear and insecurity made way for feeling bold and strong? Many years after my childhood had passed, I was rather surprised, when my mother told me that she had often felt guilty. For working, for being late sometimes, for not being the typical perfect mum (seriously, what is that, anyway?). She told me that she had often asked herself whether we (my sisters and me) reproached her for it. I was honestly surprised, because I had never blamed her for that. No, not even secretly. Mum and Dad work. Equally. Quite the contrary. Today, I am grateful to her for raising me as the strong and autonomous woman that I am. I am grateful that she has always made me feel like being able and worthy to do anything I want, if I work hard for it. More than that - I am grateful to her for living these values. Being the oldest of three sisters, it was a completely unheard-of concept for me that, for whichever dubious reasons, I should be less worthy or les  capable of achieving the same as a boy (duh!?). Mum and Dad work equally - this is my sense of 'normal'. Because neither of them will receive their paycheck for free, nor will they get their groceries from the supermarket for free. By the way, my Mum earns more than my Dad. It was only much later that I had to learn that for some people, this is offensive (?!#*!) On a side note, I am also grateful to my Mum for teaching me how to prepare a halfway healthy dinner in only 10 minutes, if time is short yet again. And that everybody is happier and more satisfied when, instead, you spend some quality time with the family and joke around. Yep, they don't teach you that at school. The 'perfect mother' is a myth Dear working mum, trust me, it's all going to be fine. Your child will have plenty of opportunities to temporarily hate you - puberty, I'm looking at you - and having picked them up too late from kindergarden will really be the least of your worries. There's no way for you to avert that, even if you were always the first to pick them up, with a toothpaste-commercial-smile on your lips. No, not even if you always bring homemade chocolate cookies. And there is one more thing, dear working mum colleague. One thing that I already new before, but which you are proving to the world every day, namely that having a family does not make you less productive, or less dedicated, nor lazy. On the contrary: time pressure is the best way to increase efficiency and learn how to better prioritise. You don't waste time in pointless meetings or with any unimportant nitty-gritty bullshit. You tackle the real stuff; you do it now, and with highest efficiency - because when the working day is over, you have more important things to do than sitting in a dark office and working endless unpaid overtime. I advocate for pride, not guilt! Dear working mum, please stop blaming yourself. Don't make yourself believe that you are never 'good enough', be it at work or at home. Because you are. Instead, be proud that you lead by example. That you show your children and all of us that life is not over, just because you have kids. That you show your employer, against all prejudices, that people with children don't cease to be full-fledged and valuable team members (this is such an obvious point that I feel silly to even have to say that). My Mum is just like you. She also had these feelings of guilt - while I was happily and contentedly eating my melted cheese sandwiches and doing what was my job: growing up, finding my place in this world, and watch cartoons every now and again. All's well that ends well I would have never even thought about being mad at my mother for all this. No, in all modesty, I think she did a pretty good job, I turned out quite ok, didn't I. Had she committed herself to me and only me 24/7 - that wouldn't have helped to eliminate my many flaws and shortcomings. In fact, I think I would have even more of them. Today I just know one thing: I would be happy, if one day I did just half as good a job as she does - or you or all the other women out there. Happy International Women's Day, dear mothers! &amp;nbsp;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Job hunting via LinkedIn? 10 tips for young professionals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/job-hunting-via-linkedin-10-tips-young-professionals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Job hunting via LinkedIn? 10 tips for young professionals" /><published>2018-01-28T21:16:59+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-28T21:16:59+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/job-hunting-via-linkedin-10-tips-young-professionals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/job-hunting-via-linkedin-10-tips-young-professionals/">&lt;p&gt;When I first signed up for LinkedIn - I believe it was towards the end of my Bachelors degree - I didn’t really know why I was doing this, I mean, what I would use it for. In my eyes it was yet another social platform, that I would have to maintain and update. The mere thought of it was exhausting me already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the end I thought: whatever, there's no harm in giving it a try, is there? Some of my friends from University already had profiles, so at least I wouldn’t have zero contacts, but rather... well, three. And with time, my profile evolved, and I gained not only new contacts and additional milestones on my CV, but today I even owe my present job to this portal. My current employer had stumbled upon my page - and then offered me a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I put together some recommendations that could help you to create and polish your LinkedIn presence – in 10 easy-to-follow steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;#1 Number one: just start already&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the readers of this blog will already have mastered this one. Congratulations! If not, what are you waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re still at university, don't hesitate to get the ball rolling on your LinkedIn profile. Needless to say, one should be able to find your profile by searching for your real name. A protected account which is only be visible for you and your friends may be useful for Instagram if you want to protect your privacy. But on LinkedIn that more or less defeats the purpose. Firstly, you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;to be found, and secondly you’d be sharing exclusively things that would make you look good professionally, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p3&quot;&gt;#2 What do you write? Reflect on your professional experience so far (even if it’s not a lot yet)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, for me this was one of the main advantages of my new social media toy: I was forced to review my almost non-existent career and think about all the things I've done so far, what I was proud of and how I could present it in the best way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes my studies, what do I want to highlight, in order to try and impress someone? What have I achieved, professionally? My first reflex was to say: well, nothing, I’m only just studying! But after giving it some proper thought, I realised that I had indeed already done and achieved a couple of things that I could be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sit down for an afternoon and write down all the things that you have done professionally. Maybe you could do that together with a friend? A well-meaning second opinion can work wonders sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fair amount of stalking is allowed, too: browse through some other people’s profiles, including those that are in a similar situation as you. When you see what other students or young professionals are bragging about, it can remind you of one or another activity that you had almost forgotten about. This could be anything from summer jobs over volunteer activities to internships – anything that is remotely related to your “professional you”. Did you participate in any competitions? Any programmes, scholarships, study visits abroad? Especially when you’re at the beginning of your career and don’t have so many things to show off with, include whatever you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you member of some network, an organisation or a local non-profit? Add it in and describe your role in it. If that organisation has a LinkedIn-group, join it. Did you publish any academic papers during your studies? Did you write for your university newspaper? Put it all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these things are not simply filling the emptiness in your yet-to-mature career path. They also show that you are interested and competent to do things. And, very importantly, these little tricks of the trade can help you to become more confident with what you have done so far, as well as to get a better feel for what is relevant for your career path and how to present it in the best possible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;#3 How do you name your various milestones?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only because you were an &quot;intern in unit 3.24b“, and that's what is indicated in your work contract, it doesn’t mean that you have to describe it like this. Unless you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;to prevent people from understanding what it is that you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously: lying is a no-go. But still, there are many ways to describe your position and tasks in a more understandable way. When I was filling my empty LinkedIn-profile for the first time, I was a student at university - fair enough. But I was also doing some freelance translation jobs on the side from time to time. Therefore, it was not a lie to call myself a freelance translator, as well as student right? (Even if the good old impostor-syndrome made me feel slightly uncomfortable with it, but I simply had to get over that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could do the same if you are for example volunteering in some NGO or doing jobs on the side on a freelance basis. Moreover, providing more than one “position” at the same time is perfectly acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example: when talking about their traineeship, many of my friends simply put “intern” and the company’s name, and leave it there. While this may be factually correct, it remains incredibly vague about what you actually did. As far as this description is concerned, your tasks and responsibilities could have ranged from making coffee all day or taking care of entire operations all by yourself – who could tell? We all know perfectly well that all too often, interns are used as cheap and docile workers. Which is why it is all the more important to choose a description for your experience, which explains in the best possible way what your actual tasks and responsibilities were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, halfway through one of my traineeships, I eventually had to de-facto replace a colleague, who was out for several months. My job title, as defined by my contract, remained unchanged, but my actual duties had evolved massively. Therefore, changing my LinkedIn-description to “Press assistant (trainee)” is no less factually correct than “intern” – yet it looks more impressive and represents my tasks better. You could also chose to name your department, e.g. “Information and media (trainee) or “Trainee in the controlling department of XYZ”, etc. There’s no strict rules really, as long as it reflects the truth and provides a hint about what you have been actually doing there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p2&quot;&gt;#4 List your tasks and responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever experience you list, make sure to make use of the description box. Give the person looking at your profile a chance to better understand your role and concrete tasks. An example from my work experience would be: drafting press material, organising press conferences, briefing journalists, etc. etc. By naming some typical duties, you are showing that you are indeed familiar with these tasks, should a potential employer look for someone to do just that for them. You could also name the kinds of tools and programmes that you have used there, if that is relevant in your sector. One advantage that young professionals tend to have over their more experienced and older counterparts, is that they excel at digital skills. Make sure to let people know about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, what kinds of projects have you taken ownership for? Which topics have you worked on in greater detail? If it helps to describe your professional experience, use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;#5 Dress for the job you want, not for the one you have&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, we all have to do different tasks in parallel. Some of them we like doing, some of them we hate. When describing your professional experience, you should primarily name the ones that you like doing, and of which you would like to do even more in your future job. When somebody is browsing through LinkedIn for potential staff to hire, they may type in certain keywords, for example “controlling”, “website maintenance” or “events organisation”. If you are currently doing a bit of all of these, but want to never waste a single second of your life with controlling – leave it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If instead, you are sometimes organising events, but feel like this is what you would want to be doing all day long, make sure this is included in your description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The same holds true for your city of residence:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If currently you are living in Brussels, but would like to move to Berlin, I recommend you to change your city of residence to the latter. This way you will firstly receive vacancy recommendations for your preferred city and secondly, employers who are hiring will potentially see your profile when looking for suitable people in that area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-4940 size-large&quot; title=&quot;LinkedIn Jobsuche&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Bildschirmfoto-2017-05-15-um-22.22.26-1024x583.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;583&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p2&quot;&gt;#6 Who should you connect with?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is very simple: with as many people as possible – provided that you actually know them (or have a good reason to contact them even though you don’t know them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with people from your school or university. The friend you beat at beer-pong today could be the HR-person of the company you’re trying to get in to tomorrow. I’m not saying you should suck up to everyone you meet, just in case you might need their help later. But loosely keeping in touch won’t do any harm and allows you to stay up-to-date on who is where. In the best case it can even help in unforeseen ways, like learning about vacancies earlier because one of your contacts posted it, etc. During any internship or job you should definitely connect with colleagues, bosses or business partners there. Sticking around in people’s list of LinkedIn connections can help them to remember you. Sometimes people need new staff at very short notice – it is not unheard of that they are willing to recruit people from their existing pool of contacts, such as former trainees and the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also want to connect with people you meet at conferences or other events, if, say, you had an interesting conversation with them. Maybe you shared some interests, or that person works in a company or an sector you are very interested in? Try to talk to them and then connect via LinkedIn to stay in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very importantly though: when adding them, do leave a short note saying who you are and where you met – not everyone is super good with remembering names and faces, and you don’t want to confuse people and have them ignore you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p3&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-4939 size-large&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Bildschirmfoto-2017-05-15-um-22.20.29-1024x546.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;546&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p3&quot;&gt;#7 Skills &amp;amp; Endorsements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On LinkedIn you have the possibility to compliment people for their competencies or leave a short message stating how they excelled at this or the other. This is not a must, but there’s no harm in endorsing a couple of friends or colleagues for their skills - they may return the favour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about which skills are important for your preferred career path and ask a couple of friends to endorse you for these. Firstly, this way the box will not be completely empty any more, and secondly, should anyone search for these keywords, your profile might even show up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter wp-image-4938 size-large&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Bildschirmfoto-2017-05-15-um-22.16.16-1024x575.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;575&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;#8 And now, post until you drop?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;With all the social media profiles that I have to maintain, I hardly manage to stay up-to-date on all of them, let alone to post interesting and intelligent contributions all the time. However, should you have the energy and motivation for it, it is indeed a fine opportunity to let people know what you care about and how you get involved. The same goes for articles that you write. Make sure to let your network know about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-4941&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Bildschirmfoto-2017-05-15-um-22.25.07-1024x611.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;611&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;#9 LinkedIn-Hygiene - update it from time to time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time (and your career) progresses, new milestones and experiences will add to your CV. Updating this whenever something changes in your professional life really doesn’t take long. A new traineeship, a new NGO you joined, a new job you started or a new language you are learning. Just add it in. It’s not complicated, it just needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when I speak to people about LinkedIn and the like, they share their bad conscience: “Oh boy, I really should have a look at my profile and update it”. This makes it sound like a whole lot of work, but it really isn’t. At the very least, your given position on LinkedIn should reflect the actual job that you’re currently doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;p4&quot;&gt;#10 So, why should I be doing all of this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you want to find your next dream job via LinkedIn or not - you should probably put some thinking into your digital profile &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt;you desperately need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very satisfied with my previous job. And even if I somewhat knew that I wouldn’t stay there forever, I wasn’t actively looking for something new. But my LinkedIn profile had different plans for me, and was working behind the scenes to get me hired in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It came totally out of the blue, when I received that email from a former colleague. We had never worked with each other directly, but I had added him on LinkedIn when I was a trainee there back in 2013. “We’re looking for people like you”, he wrote. “If you’re interested, feel free to send me your CV. What do you say?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say: Seriously, investing a little bit of energy in your LinkedIn profile is totally worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about you?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you maintaining your digital profile with care? Did you ever use it to hunt for jobs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have any other recommendations that I missed here? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">When I first signed up for LinkedIn - I believe it was towards the end of my Bachelors degree - I didn’t really know why I was doing this, I mean, what I would use it for. In my eyes it was yet another social platform, that I would have to maintain and update. The mere thought of it was exhausting me already. But in the end I thought: whatever, there's no harm in giving it a try, is there? Some of my friends from University already had profiles, so at least I wouldn’t have zero contacts, but rather... well, three. And with time, my profile evolved, and I gained not only new contacts and additional milestones on my CV, but today I even owe my present job to this portal. My current employer had stumbled upon my page - and then offered me a job. In this article I put together some recommendations that could help you to create and polish your LinkedIn presence – in 10 easy-to-follow steps. #1 Number one: just start already Most of the readers of this blog will already have mastered this one. Congratulations! If not, what are you waiting for? Even if you’re still at university, don't hesitate to get the ball rolling on your LinkedIn profile. Needless to say, one should be able to find your profile by searching for your real name. A protected account which is only be visible for you and your friends may be useful for Instagram if you want to protect your privacy. But on LinkedIn that more or less defeats the purpose. Firstly, you wantto be found, and secondly you’d be sharing exclusively things that would make you look good professionally, right? #2 What do you write? Reflect on your professional experience so far (even if it’s not a lot yet) Back then, for me this was one of the main advantages of my new social media toy: I was forced to review my almost non-existent career and think about all the things I've done so far, what I was proud of and how I could present it in the best way possible. When it comes my studies, what do I want to highlight, in order to try and impress someone? What have I achieved, professionally? My first reflex was to say: well, nothing, I’m only just studying! But after giving it some proper thought, I realised that I had indeed already done and achieved a couple of things that I could be proud of. Sit down for an afternoon and write down all the things that you have done professionally. Maybe you could do that together with a friend? A well-meaning second opinion can work wonders sometimes. A fair amount of stalking is allowed, too: browse through some other people’s profiles, including those that are in a similar situation as you. When you see what other students or young professionals are bragging about, it can remind you of one or another activity that you had almost forgotten about. This could be anything from summer jobs over volunteer activities to internships – anything that is remotely related to your “professional you”. Did you participate in any competitions? Any programmes, scholarships, study visits abroad? Especially when you’re at the beginning of your career and don’t have so many things to show off with, include whatever you can. Are you member of some network, an organisation or a local non-profit? Add it in and describe your role in it. If that organisation has a LinkedIn-group, join it. Did you publish any academic papers during your studies? Did you write for your university newspaper? Put it all in. All these things are not simply filling the emptiness in your yet-to-mature career path. They also show that you are interested and competent to do things. And, very importantly, these little tricks of the trade can help you to become more confident with what you have done so far, as well as to get a better feel for what is relevant for your career path and how to present it in the best possible way. #3 How do you name your various milestones? Only because you were an &quot;intern in unit 3.24b“, and that's what is indicated in your work contract, it doesn’t mean that you have to describe it like this. Unless you wantto prevent people from understanding what it is that you do. Obviously: lying is a no-go. But still, there are many ways to describe your position and tasks in a more understandable way. When I was filling my empty LinkedIn-profile for the first time, I was a student at university - fair enough. But I was also doing some freelance translation jobs on the side from time to time. Therefore, it was not a lie to call myself a freelance translator, as well as student right? (Even if the good old impostor-syndrome made me feel slightly uncomfortable with it, but I simply had to get over that). You could do the same if you are for example volunteering in some NGO or doing jobs on the side on a freelance basis. Moreover, providing more than one “position” at the same time is perfectly acceptable. Another example: when talking about their traineeship, many of my friends simply put “intern” and the company’s name, and leave it there. While this may be factually correct, it remains incredibly vague about what you actually did. As far as this description is concerned, your tasks and responsibilities could have ranged from making coffee all day or taking care of entire operations all by yourself – who could tell? We all know perfectly well that all too often, interns are used as cheap and docile workers. Which is why it is all the more important to choose a description for your experience, which explains in the best possible way what your actual tasks and responsibilities were. For instance, halfway through one of my traineeships, I eventually had to de-facto replace a colleague, who was out for several months. My job title, as defined by my contract, remained unchanged, but my actual duties had evolved massively. Therefore, changing my LinkedIn-description to “Press assistant (trainee)” is no less factually correct than “intern” – yet it looks more impressive and represents my tasks better. You could also chose to name your department, e.g. “Information and media (trainee) or “Trainee in the controlling department of XYZ”, etc. There’s no strict rules really, as long as it reflects the truth and provides a hint about what you have been actually doing there. #4 List your tasks and responsibilities Whichever experience you list, make sure to make use of the description box. Give the person looking at your profile a chance to better understand your role and concrete tasks. An example from my work experience would be: drafting press material, organising press conferences, briefing journalists, etc. etc. By naming some typical duties, you are showing that you are indeed familiar with these tasks, should a potential employer look for someone to do just that for them. You could also name the kinds of tools and programmes that you have used there, if that is relevant in your sector. One advantage that young professionals tend to have over their more experienced and older counterparts, is that they excel at digital skills. Make sure to let people know about that. Further, what kinds of projects have you taken ownership for? Which topics have you worked on in greater detail? If it helps to describe your professional experience, use it. #5 Dress for the job you want, not for the one you have Sure, we all have to do different tasks in parallel. Some of them we like doing, some of them we hate. When describing your professional experience, you should primarily name the ones that you like doing, and of which you would like to do even more in your future job. When somebody is browsing through LinkedIn for potential staff to hire, they may type in certain keywords, for example “controlling”, “website maintenance” or “events organisation”. If you are currently doing a bit of all of these, but want to never waste a single second of your life with controlling – leave it out. If instead, you are sometimes organising events, but feel like this is what you would want to be doing all day long, make sure this is included in your description. The same holds true for your city of residence: If currently you are living in Brussels, but would like to move to Berlin, I recommend you to change your city of residence to the latter. This way you will firstly receive vacancy recommendations for your preferred city and secondly, employers who are hiring will potentially see your profile when looking for suitable people in that area. #6 Who should you connect with? This one is very simple: with as many people as possible – provided that you actually know them (or have a good reason to contact them even though you don’t know them). Start with people from your school or university. The friend you beat at beer-pong today could be the HR-person of the company you’re trying to get in to tomorrow. I’m not saying you should suck up to everyone you meet, just in case you might need their help later. But loosely keeping in touch won’t do any harm and allows you to stay up-to-date on who is where. In the best case it can even help in unforeseen ways, like learning about vacancies earlier because one of your contacts posted it, etc. During any internship or job you should definitely connect with colleagues, bosses or business partners there. Sticking around in people’s list of LinkedIn connections can help them to remember you. Sometimes people need new staff at very short notice – it is not unheard of that they are willing to recruit people from their existing pool of contacts, such as former trainees and the like. You may also want to connect with people you meet at conferences or other events, if, say, you had an interesting conversation with them. Maybe you shared some interests, or that person works in a company or an sector you are very interested in? Try to talk to them and then connect via LinkedIn to stay in touch. Very importantly though: when adding them, do leave a short note saying who you are and where you met – not everyone is super good with remembering names and faces, and you don’t want to confuse people and have them ignore you. #7 Skills &amp;amp; Endorsements On LinkedIn you have the possibility to compliment people for their competencies or leave a short message stating how they excelled at this or the other. This is not a must, but there’s no harm in endorsing a couple of friends or colleagues for their skills - they may return the favour. Think about which skills are important for your preferred career path and ask a couple of friends to endorse you for these. Firstly, this way the box will not be completely empty any more, and secondly, should anyone search for these keywords, your profile might even show up. #8 And now, post until you drop? With all the social media profiles that I have to maintain, I hardly manage to stay up-to-date on all of them, let alone to post interesting and intelligent contributions all the time. However, should you have the energy and motivation for it, it is indeed a fine opportunity to let people know what you care about and how you get involved. The same goes for articles that you write. Make sure to let your network know about them. #9 LinkedIn-Hygiene - update it from time to time As time (and your career) progresses, new milestones and experiences will add to your CV. Updating this whenever something changes in your professional life really doesn’t take long. A new traineeship, a new NGO you joined, a new job you started or a new language you are learning. Just add it in. It’s not complicated, it just needs to be done. Sometimes when I speak to people about LinkedIn and the like, they share their bad conscience: “Oh boy, I really should have a look at my profile and update it”. This makes it sound like a whole lot of work, but it really isn’t. At the very least, your given position on LinkedIn should reflect the actual job that you’re currently doing. #10 So, why should I be doing all of this? Whether you want to find your next dream job via LinkedIn or not - you should probably put some thinking into your digital profile beforeyou desperately need it. I was very satisfied with my previous job. And even if I somewhat knew that I wouldn’t stay there forever, I wasn’t actively looking for something new. But my LinkedIn profile had different plans for me, and was working behind the scenes to get me hired in Brussels. It came totally out of the blue, when I received that email from a former colleague. We had never worked with each other directly, but I had added him on LinkedIn when I was a trainee there back in 2013. “We’re looking for people like you”, he wrote. “If you’re interested, feel free to send me your CV. What do you say?” I say: Seriously, investing a little bit of energy in your LinkedIn profile is totally worth it. What about you? Are you maintaining your digital profile with care? Did you ever use it to hunt for jobs? Do you have any other recommendations that I missed here? Let me know!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Tipps, wie dein neues Praktikum zum Erfolg wird</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/4-tipps-wie-dein-neues-praktikum-zum-erfolg-wird/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Tipps, wie dein neues Praktikum zum Erfolg wird" /><published>2017-11-06T07:14:59+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-06T07:14:59+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/4-tipps-wie-dein-neues-praktikum-zum-erfolg-wird</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/4-tipps-wie-dein-neues-praktikum-zum-erfolg-wird/">&lt;p&gt;Während meiner Studienzeit habe ich zwei Praktika absolviert. Das eine unterbezahlt, das andere gleich ganz unbezahlt. Aber hey, in der Not frisst der &lt;del&gt;Teufel, äh,&lt;/del&gt; Berufseinsteiger Fliegen, und &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/hilfe-ich-bin-erwachsen-oder-das-ende-meiner-bafoeg-saga/&quot;&gt;dank BAFöG&lt;/a&gt; hatte ich keine größeren Existenzängste. Ich konnte also ein bisschen ausprobieren und Berufsluft schnuppern. Denn seien wir ehrlich: das Studium, das einen adäquat auf das Berufsleben vorbereitet, muss erst noch erfunden werden. Nach meinem Uni-Abschluss hatte ich dann mein bislang bestes Praktikum bei der EU-Kommission ergattert - es wurde mit €1100 für meine damaligen Verhältnisse fürstlich entlohnt! (Bewerbungen sind alle 6 Monate hier möglich).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Praktikum ist was du draus machst!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich glaube, dass ein erfolgreiches Praktikum von vier Faktoren bestimmt wird. Nicht auf alle hast du immer Einfluss, aber mindestens die Hälfte hängt zu einem großen Tail davon ab, was du daraus machst - und über 50% Gestaltungsspielraum sind echt viel! Nutze das.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;Praktikum ist was du draus machst! 4 Tipps wie dein neues #Praktikum zum Erfolg wird&quot; username=&quot;chapteronemag&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sagen wir also du hast ein tolles Praktikum ergattert und du bist motiviert, das Beste daraus zu machen. Wie geht es weiter? Welche Faktoren bestimmen also, ob dein Praktikum dich wirklich auf deinem Berufsweg weiterbringt - oder einfach nur als Lückenfüller auf deinem &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/linkedin-xing-jobsuche-10-tipps-fuer-berufseinsteiger/&quot;&gt;Lebenslauf&lt;/a&gt; verkommt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Eine halbwegs faire Bezahlung&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eins ist klar: Wir machen Praktika nicht für die dicke Kohle, sondern um etwas zu lernen. Dennoch solltest du im Idealfall nachts ruhig schlafen und ab und zu deine Wohnung heizen können. Zugegeben, wenn man mal davon absieht, dass letztlich &lt;em&gt;du&lt;/em&gt; entscheidest, was du annimmst und was nicht, hast du auf diesen Punkt recht begrenzten Einfluss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicht in allen Branchen hat man den Luxus, besonders wählerisch zu sein. Wenn du verhandeln kannst, verhandle. Vielleicht kannst du ja einen Zuschuss zu &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/wenn-du-fuer-den-job-in-eine-neue-stadt-ziehst/&quot;&gt;deiner Unterkunft&lt;/a&gt;, gratis Mittagessen, oder sonstige Extras rausschlagen? Fragen kostet nichts (außer Überwindung).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und wenn das alles nicht möglich ist, stelle sicher, dass du wenigstens so viel wie möglich in deinem Praktikum lernst, um so das meiste daraus mitzunehmen. Das führt mich schon zu Punkt zwei:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Die Lerninhalte, die du geboten bekommst, und wie du eingebunden wirst&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Spoiler: nach 6 Monaten endlich den perfekten Kaffee kochen zu können, gehört nicht dazu.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wir sind uns einig: ein &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/das-richtige-studieren/&quot;&gt;Universitätsabschluss&lt;/a&gt; alleine ist noch kein Garant dafür, dass du im Job auch wirklich zurecht kommst. Die Uni bereitet uns in den wenigsten Fällen bereits adäquat für das Berufsleben vor. Deshalb sind Praktika auch so wertvoll. Du kannst verschiedene Branchen und Optionen ausprobieren und schauen, ob das überhaupt etwas für dich ist. Auch beobachten zu können, wie die anderen so arbeiten, verschiedene Arbeitsweisen miteinander zu vergleichen und &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/routine-dein-bester-freund-im-homeoffice/&quot;&gt;deine eigene&lt;/a&gt; zu finden, kann gold wert sein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dafür ist es natürlich wichtig, dass deine Vorgesetzten und dein Team dich angemessen einbinden. Zum Großteil hängt das wohl von ihnen ab - und ja, ich weiß, wie leicht man in der Hektik des Arbeitsalltags vergisst, den Praktikanten in Kopie zu setzen. Auch ist die Versuchung manchmal groß, etwas &quot;mal eben schnell&quot; selbst zu machen, als es erst noch ewig erklären zu müssen. Aber selbstverständlich nützt das dir als Praktikant/in recht wenig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wenn du also trotz guter Absichten von &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/darf-ich-vorstellen-frau-twitter-und-herr-snapchat/&quot;&gt;deinem Team&lt;/a&gt; weniger eingebunden wirst als dir lieb wäre, rufe dich den Kollegen und Vorgesetzten gerne proaktiv, freundlich und unaufdringlich ins Gedächtnis. Frage nach Hintergrundinformationen oder Dokumenten, die dir helfen können, das Projekt besser zu verstehen. Sei kreativ, mach dir Gedanken und konkrete Vorschläge, wie du dich einbringen und ihnen Arbeit abnehmen kannst. Zum Beispiel: &quot;Im letzten Teammeeting hast du erwähnt, dass du eine Analyse von XY brauchst; ich habe mal recherchiert und etwas zusammen gestellt&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hole dir Feedback: Gerade am Anfang werden Aufgaben, die du erledigst, noch nicht ganz das sein, was gebraucht wird. Das ist ganz normal, denn jedes Team hat eine andere Arbeitsweise, und jeder Kollege einen anderen Stil. Deshalb ist es umso wichtiger, dass du dir unaufdringlich Feedback abholst, oder auch hinterher vergleichst, was von deiner Arbeit ins Endprodukt übernommen wurde. Mit der Zeit wirst du immer besser verstehen, wie du dich am besten einbringen kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Die Möglichkeit, einen Mehrwert zu bieten - idealerweise auch über die Zeit deines Praktikums hinaus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den wertvollsten Tipp, den ich als Praktikantin zu Studienzeiten von meiner Vorgesetzten bekommen habe, war: Suche dir ein Projekt für deine Zeit hier. Etwas worauf du hinarbeiten kannst, etwas was nützlich ist, und auch nach deinem Praktikum noch nützlich bleibt. Etwas, was du hinterher als deine persönliche Errungenschaft mitnimmst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nach ein paar Wochen im Praktikum wirst du hoffentlich bereits ein paar Aufgaben haben und auch besser verstanden haben, wer was wann wie braucht. Erledige deine Aufgaben so gut du kannst, und wenn du mal nichts zu tun hast, suche proaktiv und kreativ nach Dingen, die du tun könntest, um deinem Team die Arbeit zu erleichtern oder die Qualität der Arbeit zu erhöhen. Jedes, wirklich jedes Büro hat eine lange Liste von &quot;wir müssten mal&quot; oder &quot;man sollte vielleicht&quot;-Aufgaben, zu denen nie jemand wirklich kommt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat dein Team vielleicht keine anständige Social-Media-Strategie, sondern tweetet und postet immer ad-hoc? Braucht es vielleicht ein besseres Monitoring darüber, was gut klappt, und was nicht? Vielleicht eine Analyse plus Anleitung, wie und zu welchen Uhrzeiten man wann am besten twittert, postet, etc.?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/sie-war-jung-und-brauchte-das-geld/&quot;&gt;Du bist jung&lt;/a&gt; und hast sau-viele Kompetenzen, die deine Kollegen möglicherweise nicht haben. Digitales und &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/sascha-boehr-probleme-loesen/&quot;&gt;Social Media&lt;/a&gt; sind die ersten Dinge, die mir gerade in den Sinn kommen, aber da gibt es ganz sicher einiges! Du hast den Luxus, dass du erstens noch nicht betriebsblind bist, und zweitens Zeit hast, zu recherchieren und dir Gedanken zu machen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bespreche deine Ideen mit deinem Vorgesetzten und/oder Kollegen und entwickle etwas, was einen klaren Mehrwert für die tägliche Arbeit hat, und im Idealfall sogar nach deiner Zeit als Praktikant noch verwendet wird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Was du für die Zeit danach mitnimmst&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denke an die Zeit nach deinem Praktikum, wenn du dann nämlich anfängst &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/generation-praktikum-und-die-bewerbung/&quot;&gt;Bewerbungen für richtige Jobs&lt;/a&gt; zu schreiben. Jeder weiß, dass es unter Praktikanten zwei Extreme gibt: diejenigen, die faul rumlümmeln und das Ende der 6 Monate abwarten, und solche, die sich zu fast vollwertigen Mitarbeitern entwickeln, die proaktiv sind, und Verantwortung übertragen bekommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sammle Argumente, mit denen du zeigst, dass du zur zweiten Sorte gehörst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welches sind die gängigen Fragen, die man in Jobinterviews bekommt? &quot;Was sind deine größten Erfolge aus deinem bisherigen Berufsleben?&quot; &quot;Welche Projekte hast du bereits erfolgreich umgesetzt?&quot; &quot;Welche schwierigen Herausforderungen hast du im Beruf gemeistert, und wie hast du das gemacht?&quot; ...und so weiter. Nur weil du noch keine 15 Jahre Berufserfahrung hast, bedeutet das nicht, dass du diese Fragen nicht mit konkreten Beispielen beantworten kannst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mache über die Zeit deines Praktikums eine Liste mit Aufgaben, die du erfolgreich gemeistert hast, und für die du ein bisschen Verantwortung übernommen hast. Mach dir Notizen, damit du das alles nicht vergisst. Das schlimmste Gefühl ist, wenn du bei deiner nächsten Bewerbung vor einem leeren Word-Dokument sitzt, und dir auf Teufel-komm-raus nicht einfallen will, wo du die ganzen Kompetenzen und Erfahrungen, die in der Stellenanzeige gefordert werden, erworben und bereits angewendet hast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tipps dazu, wie du deine Arbeitserfahrung als Praktikant am besten ins rechte Licht rückst, habe ich hier aufgeschrieben: &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/generation-praktikum-und-die-bewerbung/&quot;&gt;Generation Praktikum und die Bewerbung als Ex-Praktikant.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das allerwichtigste: Glaub an dich und deine Fähigkeiten. Du machst das schon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sonst noch was?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Habe ich etwas wichtiges vergessen? Hast du weitere Tipps? Was sind deine Erfahrungen mit Praktika? Schreib es in die Kommentare und lass es uns wissen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ach ja, und erzähl's weiter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[bctt tweet=&quot;4 Tipps, wie dein neues #Praktikum zum Erfolg wird&quot; username=&quot;chapteronemag&quot;]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><category term="Arbeit" /><category term="Berufserfahrung" /><category term="Erfolg" /><category term="Feedback" /><category term="Praktikant" /><category term="Praktikum" /><category term="Student" /><category term="Studium" /><category term="Tipps" /><summary type="html">Während meiner Studienzeit habe ich zwei Praktika absolviert. Das eine unterbezahlt, das andere gleich ganz unbezahlt. Aber hey, in der Not frisst der Teufel, äh, Berufseinsteiger Fliegen, und dank BAFöG hatte ich keine größeren Existenzängste. Ich konnte also ein bisschen ausprobieren und Berufsluft schnuppern. Denn seien wir ehrlich: das Studium, das einen adäquat auf das Berufsleben vorbereitet, muss erst noch erfunden werden. Nach meinem Uni-Abschluss hatte ich dann mein bislang bestes Praktikum bei der EU-Kommission ergattert - es wurde mit €1100 für meine damaligen Verhältnisse fürstlich entlohnt! (Bewerbungen sind alle 6 Monate hier möglich). Praktikum ist was du draus machst! Ich glaube, dass ein erfolgreiches Praktikum von vier Faktoren bestimmt wird. Nicht auf alle hast du immer Einfluss, aber mindestens die Hälfte hängt zu einem großen Tail davon ab, was du daraus machst - und über 50% Gestaltungsspielraum sind echt viel! Nutze das. [bctt tweet=&quot;Praktikum ist was du draus machst! 4 Tipps wie dein neues #Praktikum zum Erfolg wird&quot; username=&quot;chapteronemag&quot;] Sagen wir also du hast ein tolles Praktikum ergattert und du bist motiviert, das Beste daraus zu machen. Wie geht es weiter? Welche Faktoren bestimmen also, ob dein Praktikum dich wirklich auf deinem Berufsweg weiterbringt - oder einfach nur als Lückenfüller auf deinem Lebenslauf verkommt? 1. Eine halbwegs faire Bezahlung Eins ist klar: Wir machen Praktika nicht für die dicke Kohle, sondern um etwas zu lernen. Dennoch solltest du im Idealfall nachts ruhig schlafen und ab und zu deine Wohnung heizen können. Zugegeben, wenn man mal davon absieht, dass letztlich du entscheidest, was du annimmst und was nicht, hast du auf diesen Punkt recht begrenzten Einfluss. Nicht in allen Branchen hat man den Luxus, besonders wählerisch zu sein. Wenn du verhandeln kannst, verhandle. Vielleicht kannst du ja einen Zuschuss zu deiner Unterkunft, gratis Mittagessen, oder sonstige Extras rausschlagen? Fragen kostet nichts (außer Überwindung). Und wenn das alles nicht möglich ist, stelle sicher, dass du wenigstens so viel wie möglich in deinem Praktikum lernst, um so das meiste daraus mitzunehmen. Das führt mich schon zu Punkt zwei: 2. Die Lerninhalte, die du geboten bekommst, und wie du eingebunden wirst (Spoiler: nach 6 Monaten endlich den perfekten Kaffee kochen zu können, gehört nicht dazu.) Wir sind uns einig: ein Universitätsabschluss alleine ist noch kein Garant dafür, dass du im Job auch wirklich zurecht kommst. Die Uni bereitet uns in den wenigsten Fällen bereits adäquat für das Berufsleben vor. Deshalb sind Praktika auch so wertvoll. Du kannst verschiedene Branchen und Optionen ausprobieren und schauen, ob das überhaupt etwas für dich ist. Auch beobachten zu können, wie die anderen so arbeiten, verschiedene Arbeitsweisen miteinander zu vergleichen und deine eigene zu finden, kann gold wert sein. Dafür ist es natürlich wichtig, dass deine Vorgesetzten und dein Team dich angemessen einbinden. Zum Großteil hängt das wohl von ihnen ab - und ja, ich weiß, wie leicht man in der Hektik des Arbeitsalltags vergisst, den Praktikanten in Kopie zu setzen. Auch ist die Versuchung manchmal groß, etwas &quot;mal eben schnell&quot; selbst zu machen, als es erst noch ewig erklären zu müssen. Aber selbstverständlich nützt das dir als Praktikant/in recht wenig. Wenn du also trotz guter Absichten von deinem Team weniger eingebunden wirst als dir lieb wäre, rufe dich den Kollegen und Vorgesetzten gerne proaktiv, freundlich und unaufdringlich ins Gedächtnis. Frage nach Hintergrundinformationen oder Dokumenten, die dir helfen können, das Projekt besser zu verstehen. Sei kreativ, mach dir Gedanken und konkrete Vorschläge, wie du dich einbringen und ihnen Arbeit abnehmen kannst. Zum Beispiel: &quot;Im letzten Teammeeting hast du erwähnt, dass du eine Analyse von XY brauchst; ich habe mal recherchiert und etwas zusammen gestellt&quot;. Hole dir Feedback: Gerade am Anfang werden Aufgaben, die du erledigst, noch nicht ganz das sein, was gebraucht wird. Das ist ganz normal, denn jedes Team hat eine andere Arbeitsweise, und jeder Kollege einen anderen Stil. Deshalb ist es umso wichtiger, dass du dir unaufdringlich Feedback abholst, oder auch hinterher vergleichst, was von deiner Arbeit ins Endprodukt übernommen wurde. Mit der Zeit wirst du immer besser verstehen, wie du dich am besten einbringen kannst. 3. Die Möglichkeit, einen Mehrwert zu bieten - idealerweise auch über die Zeit deines Praktikums hinaus Den wertvollsten Tipp, den ich als Praktikantin zu Studienzeiten von meiner Vorgesetzten bekommen habe, war: Suche dir ein Projekt für deine Zeit hier. Etwas worauf du hinarbeiten kannst, etwas was nützlich ist, und auch nach deinem Praktikum noch nützlich bleibt. Etwas, was du hinterher als deine persönliche Errungenschaft mitnimmst. Nach ein paar Wochen im Praktikum wirst du hoffentlich bereits ein paar Aufgaben haben und auch besser verstanden haben, wer was wann wie braucht. Erledige deine Aufgaben so gut du kannst, und wenn du mal nichts zu tun hast, suche proaktiv und kreativ nach Dingen, die du tun könntest, um deinem Team die Arbeit zu erleichtern oder die Qualität der Arbeit zu erhöhen. Jedes, wirklich jedes Büro hat eine lange Liste von &quot;wir müssten mal&quot; oder &quot;man sollte vielleicht&quot;-Aufgaben, zu denen nie jemand wirklich kommt. Hat dein Team vielleicht keine anständige Social-Media-Strategie, sondern tweetet und postet immer ad-hoc? Braucht es vielleicht ein besseres Monitoring darüber, was gut klappt, und was nicht? Vielleicht eine Analyse plus Anleitung, wie und zu welchen Uhrzeiten man wann am besten twittert, postet, etc.? Du bist jung und hast sau-viele Kompetenzen, die deine Kollegen möglicherweise nicht haben. Digitales und Social Media sind die ersten Dinge, die mir gerade in den Sinn kommen, aber da gibt es ganz sicher einiges! Du hast den Luxus, dass du erstens noch nicht betriebsblind bist, und zweitens Zeit hast, zu recherchieren und dir Gedanken zu machen. Bespreche deine Ideen mit deinem Vorgesetzten und/oder Kollegen und entwickle etwas, was einen klaren Mehrwert für die tägliche Arbeit hat, und im Idealfall sogar nach deiner Zeit als Praktikant noch verwendet wird. 4. Was du für die Zeit danach mitnimmst Denke an die Zeit nach deinem Praktikum, wenn du dann nämlich anfängst Bewerbungen für richtige Jobs zu schreiben. Jeder weiß, dass es unter Praktikanten zwei Extreme gibt: diejenigen, die faul rumlümmeln und das Ende der 6 Monate abwarten, und solche, die sich zu fast vollwertigen Mitarbeitern entwickeln, die proaktiv sind, und Verantwortung übertragen bekommen. Sammle Argumente, mit denen du zeigst, dass du zur zweiten Sorte gehörst. Welches sind die gängigen Fragen, die man in Jobinterviews bekommt? &quot;Was sind deine größten Erfolge aus deinem bisherigen Berufsleben?&quot; &quot;Welche Projekte hast du bereits erfolgreich umgesetzt?&quot; &quot;Welche schwierigen Herausforderungen hast du im Beruf gemeistert, und wie hast du das gemacht?&quot; ...und so weiter. Nur weil du noch keine 15 Jahre Berufserfahrung hast, bedeutet das nicht, dass du diese Fragen nicht mit konkreten Beispielen beantworten kannst. Mache über die Zeit deines Praktikums eine Liste mit Aufgaben, die du erfolgreich gemeistert hast, und für die du ein bisschen Verantwortung übernommen hast. Mach dir Notizen, damit du das alles nicht vergisst. Das schlimmste Gefühl ist, wenn du bei deiner nächsten Bewerbung vor einem leeren Word-Dokument sitzt, und dir auf Teufel-komm-raus nicht einfallen will, wo du die ganzen Kompetenzen und Erfahrungen, die in der Stellenanzeige gefordert werden, erworben und bereits angewendet hast. Tipps dazu, wie du deine Arbeitserfahrung als Praktikant am besten ins rechte Licht rückst, habe ich hier aufgeschrieben: Generation Praktikum und die Bewerbung als Ex-Praktikant. Das allerwichtigste: Glaub an dich und deine Fähigkeiten. Du machst das schon. Sonst noch was? Habe ich etwas wichtiges vergessen? Hast du weitere Tipps? Was sind deine Erfahrungen mit Praktika? Schreib es in die Kommentare und lass es uns wissen. Ach ja, und erzähl's weiter: [bctt tweet=&quot;4 Tipps, wie dein neues #Praktikum zum Erfolg wird&quot; username=&quot;chapteronemag&quot;]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Mein Wunsch? Mit meinem Unternehmen nach Europa und dann die Welt!”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mein-wunsch-mit-meinem-unternehmen-nach-europa-und-dann-die-welt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Mein Wunsch? Mit meinem Unternehmen nach Europa und dann die Welt!&quot;" /><published>2017-10-26T07:19:51+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-26T07:19:51+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mein-wunsch-mit-meinem-unternehmen-nach-europa-und-dann-die-welt</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mein-wunsch-mit-meinem-unternehmen-nach-europa-und-dann-die-welt/">&lt;p&gt;Bereits über ein Jahr ist es her, als ich Aimie &lt;a href=&quot;http://chapteronemag.com/de/lieber-jeden-tag-gezielt-angehen/&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;das erste Mal interviewte&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, arbeitete sie bei Bertelsmann und war Gründerin und Geschäftsführerin von FIELFALT, einem Blogazine mit Themen rund um Beruf, Familie, Persönlichkeitsentwicklung, Liebe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damals hat sie davon berichtet, wie es für sie war, Arbeit und Studium unter einen Hut bringen zu müssen, für ihren beruflichen Weg alle 3 Monate deutschland- und weltweit umzuziehen und wie sie dabei grundsätzlich gelernt hat sich und ihre Ressourcen zu organisieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seitdem hat sich einiges getan: den Job bei Bertelsmann hat sie an den Nagel gehängt und mittlerweile &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artnight.com/#modal&quot;&gt;ArtNight&lt;/a&gt; gegründet - einem neuen kreativen Veranstaltungsformat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darüber habe ich mit ihr im Chapter One Mag-Interview #2 gesprochen: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;„Was dann geschah&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;“ sozusagen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Liebe Aimie, was machst du heute beruflich?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letzten Herbst habe ich gemeinsam mit David ArtNight gegründet; das ist eine Plattform für kreative Erlebnisse. Angefangen haben wir mit der Malerei: unsere Gäste können innerhalb von 2 Stunden, unter Anleitung eines lokalen Künstlers, ihr eigenes Kunstwerk auf Leinwand zu schaffen - und zwar in coolen Bars und Restaurants in ihrer Nähe. Wir sind inzwischen deutschlandweit und in Österreich aktiv, und das freut mich unglaublich! Denn es gibt nichts Schöneres als Menschen glücklich zu machen! Wir wecken ihre Kreativität und unterstützen Künstler, die ihr Talent nutzen und teilen können.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Online-Magazin &lt;a href=&quot;http://fielfalt.de/&quot;&gt;FIELFALT&lt;/a&gt; betreibe ich nach wie vor nebenberuflich als meinen persönlichen Blog, auf dem ich tolle Frauen portraitiere, mit dem Ziel, andere zu inspirieren. Zudem bieten wir nach wie vor die Möglichkeit an, durch unsere Unterstützung ein eigenes Netzwerk aufzubauen. Das hat mir unglaublich geholfen und mich ermutigt, selbst als Unternehmerin durchzustarten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Warum hast du dich für den beruflichen Wechsel entschieden? Was hat dich am „Neuen“ am meisten gereizt oder was hat dich am „Alten“ gestört?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es gibt Vor- und Nachteile in jeder Tätigkeit und man muss für sich selbst entscheiden, wofür das Herz schlägt. Wenn man seiner Leidenschaft nachgeht, kann man über das was “stört” viel besser hinwegsehen. Ich habe meinen Job im Großkonzern sehr geschätzt und ich habe auch unglaublich viel gelernt. Im Herzen bin ich jedoch Unternehmerin und die Motivation, mein eigenes Unternehmen aufbauen zu wollen und damit die Welt ein klein wenig zu verändern, hat schlussendlich zu meinem beruflichen Wechsel geführt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Wie sieht dein Alltag heute aus? Was ist die fundamentalste Veränderung im Gegensatz zu vorher?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Durch meine Position als Teamleiterin von einem recht großen Team, bestand mein Tag fast ausschließlich aus Besprechungen, und ich war bei vielen Themen nicht mehr im Detail involviert. Diese Meeting-Kultur wollen wir bei ArtNight ganz bewusst vermeiden. Wir starten mit einem kurzen Stand-Up-Meeting jeden Morgen, um das wichtigste für den Tag zu besprechen. Und dann arbeite ich in der Regel die wichtigsten Themen erst einmal ab. So ist man unglaublich produktiv, und jeder Tag unterscheidet sich dennoch von jedem anderen. Eine fundamentale Veränderung ist, dass wir alle Entscheidungen selbst treffen können und dadurch sehr agil arbeiten können. Das war vorher definitiv anders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Wenn du an die Zeit vor einem Jahr zurückdenkst – welche Ängste haben sich im Nichts aufgelöst, sprich: was war einfach mal halb so wild?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sätze wie “das kann ich nicht”, “das weiß ich nicht”, “das hab ich noch nie gemacht”. Als Unternehmer gibt es nur eine Lösung: Hinsetzen, sich reinfuchsen und besser machen! Es gibt nichts, worin man sich nicht einarbeiten kann - außer man trifft bewusst die Entscheidung, das nicht zu tun und zum Beispiel an einen Experten abzugeben. Das kann bei bestimmten Themen durchaus sinnvoll sein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Und was hast du im Gegenzug vielleicht unterschätzt?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Den Kundenkontakt! Ich bin ein sehr kommunikativer und extrovertierter Mensch, aber ganz direkt auf Kunden zuzugehen, seine eigene Idee zu präsentieren und sie davon zu überzeugen, war für mich am Anfang eine Herausforderung. Heute schätze ich jedes einzelne Feedback von jedem Kunden oder jeder Person mit der ich über ArtNight spreche. Ich versuche unsere Plattform dadurch jeden Tag besser zu machen!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6. Wo hast du mehr gelernt: in 5 Jahren Uni oder in den ersten paar Jahren in der Berufswelt?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich arbeite, seit ich 19 Jahre alt bin: Meinen Bachelor habe ich im dualen Studium erlangt, während des Masters immer mindestens 20 Stunden pro Woche gearbeitet - weshalb die Berufswelt bei mir immer präsent war. Ich glaube, das war eine unglaubliche Bereicherung, denn so habe ich gleich aus beiden Welten viel mitgenommen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;7. Sagen wir, du hättest einen Wunsch frei: wo ginge es als nächstes für dich hin?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beruflich: Mit ArtNight nach Europa und dann in die Welt und zwar mit mehreren Erlebnisprodukten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privat: Ich würde gern mit meinem Mann endlich eine Safari-Tour in Namibia machen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Christina Wunder</name></author><summary type="html">Bereits über ein Jahr ist es her, als ich Aimie das erste Mal interviewte, arbeitete sie bei Bertelsmann und war Gründerin und Geschäftsführerin von FIELFALT, einem Blogazine mit Themen rund um Beruf, Familie, Persönlichkeitsentwicklung, Liebe. Damals hat sie davon berichtet, wie es für sie war, Arbeit und Studium unter einen Hut bringen zu müssen, für ihren beruflichen Weg alle 3 Monate deutschland- und weltweit umzuziehen und wie sie dabei grundsätzlich gelernt hat sich und ihre Ressourcen zu organisieren. Seitdem hat sich einiges getan: den Job bei Bertelsmann hat sie an den Nagel gehängt und mittlerweile ArtNight gegründet - einem neuen kreativen Veranstaltungsformat. Darüber habe ich mit ihr im Chapter One Mag-Interview #2 gesprochen: „Was dann geschah“ sozusagen. 1. Liebe Aimie, was machst du heute beruflich? Letzten Herbst habe ich gemeinsam mit David ArtNight gegründet; das ist eine Plattform für kreative Erlebnisse. Angefangen haben wir mit der Malerei: unsere Gäste können innerhalb von 2 Stunden, unter Anleitung eines lokalen Künstlers, ihr eigenes Kunstwerk auf Leinwand zu schaffen - und zwar in coolen Bars und Restaurants in ihrer Nähe. Wir sind inzwischen deutschlandweit und in Österreich aktiv, und das freut mich unglaublich! Denn es gibt nichts Schöneres als Menschen glücklich zu machen! Wir wecken ihre Kreativität und unterstützen Künstler, die ihr Talent nutzen und teilen können. Das Online-Magazin FIELFALT betreibe ich nach wie vor nebenberuflich als meinen persönlichen Blog, auf dem ich tolle Frauen portraitiere, mit dem Ziel, andere zu inspirieren. Zudem bieten wir nach wie vor die Möglichkeit an, durch unsere Unterstützung ein eigenes Netzwerk aufzubauen. Das hat mir unglaublich geholfen und mich ermutigt, selbst als Unternehmerin durchzustarten. 2. Warum hast du dich für den beruflichen Wechsel entschieden? Was hat dich am „Neuen“ am meisten gereizt oder was hat dich am „Alten“ gestört? Es gibt Vor- und Nachteile in jeder Tätigkeit und man muss für sich selbst entscheiden, wofür das Herz schlägt. Wenn man seiner Leidenschaft nachgeht, kann man über das was “stört” viel besser hinwegsehen. Ich habe meinen Job im Großkonzern sehr geschätzt und ich habe auch unglaublich viel gelernt. Im Herzen bin ich jedoch Unternehmerin und die Motivation, mein eigenes Unternehmen aufbauen zu wollen und damit die Welt ein klein wenig zu verändern, hat schlussendlich zu meinem beruflichen Wechsel geführt. 3. Wie sieht dein Alltag heute aus? Was ist die fundamentalste Veränderung im Gegensatz zu vorher? Durch meine Position als Teamleiterin von einem recht großen Team, bestand mein Tag fast ausschließlich aus Besprechungen, und ich war bei vielen Themen nicht mehr im Detail involviert. Diese Meeting-Kultur wollen wir bei ArtNight ganz bewusst vermeiden. Wir starten mit einem kurzen Stand-Up-Meeting jeden Morgen, um das wichtigste für den Tag zu besprechen. Und dann arbeite ich in der Regel die wichtigsten Themen erst einmal ab. So ist man unglaublich produktiv, und jeder Tag unterscheidet sich dennoch von jedem anderen. Eine fundamentale Veränderung ist, dass wir alle Entscheidungen selbst treffen können und dadurch sehr agil arbeiten können. Das war vorher definitiv anders. 4. Wenn du an die Zeit vor einem Jahr zurückdenkst – welche Ängste haben sich im Nichts aufgelöst, sprich: was war einfach mal halb so wild? Sätze wie “das kann ich nicht”, “das weiß ich nicht”, “das hab ich noch nie gemacht”. Als Unternehmer gibt es nur eine Lösung: Hinsetzen, sich reinfuchsen und besser machen! Es gibt nichts, worin man sich nicht einarbeiten kann - außer man trifft bewusst die Entscheidung, das nicht zu tun und zum Beispiel an einen Experten abzugeben. Das kann bei bestimmten Themen durchaus sinnvoll sein. 5. Und was hast du im Gegenzug vielleicht unterschätzt? Den Kundenkontakt! Ich bin ein sehr kommunikativer und extrovertierter Mensch, aber ganz direkt auf Kunden zuzugehen, seine eigene Idee zu präsentieren und sie davon zu überzeugen, war für mich am Anfang eine Herausforderung. Heute schätze ich jedes einzelne Feedback von jedem Kunden oder jeder Person mit der ich über ArtNight spreche. Ich versuche unsere Plattform dadurch jeden Tag besser zu machen! 6. Wo hast du mehr gelernt: in 5 Jahren Uni oder in den ersten paar Jahren in der Berufswelt? Ich arbeite, seit ich 19 Jahre alt bin: Meinen Bachelor habe ich im dualen Studium erlangt, während des Masters immer mindestens 20 Stunden pro Woche gearbeitet - weshalb die Berufswelt bei mir immer präsent war. Ich glaube, das war eine unglaubliche Bereicherung, denn so habe ich gleich aus beiden Welten viel mitgenommen. 7. Sagen wir, du hättest einen Wunsch frei: wo ginge es als nächstes für dich hin? Beruflich: Mit ArtNight nach Europa und dann in die Welt und zwar mit mehreren Erlebnisprodukten. Privat: Ich würde gern mit meinem Mann endlich eine Safari-Tour in Namibia machen.</summary></entry></feed>